<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The grand oppressor, or the terror of tithes; first felt, and now confest: By William Erberie.</title>
            <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 143 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3226</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E671_13</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R207085</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99866157</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99866157</idno>
            <idno type="VID">118421</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 118421)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 103:E671[13])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The grand oppressor, or the terror of tithes; first felt, and now confest: By William Erberie.</title>
                  <author>Erbery, William, 1604-1654.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.D. for Giles Calvert, and are to be sold at the sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the West End of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Section beginning on p.[17] has title: "The sword doubled to cut off both the righteous and the wicked .. 1652".</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 21".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tithes --  Great Britain --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Enrique Valdive</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118421:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE Grand Oppreſſor, Or, The Terror of TITHES; Firſt FELT, and now CONFEST:</p>
                  <p>By WILLIAM ERBERIE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1652.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118421:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:118421:2"/>
                  <head>The Sum of a Letter written to one of the Commiſsioners in <hi>South-Wales, Aprill</hi> 19. 1652.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>OU willed me to write unto you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the hundred pound which you were pleaſed to promiſe preſent paiment of, if your Treaſury were not empty:</p>
                  <p>But ſince I ſaw you laſt, the Lord ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo terribly unto me, that (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>torn the caul of my heart</hi>) he diſcovered the hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie and covetouſneſſe that lay hid,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 13.8.</note> and cloſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in my fleſh.</p>
                  <p>That which brought it forth (next to the eternal ſpirit and everlaſting burnings within me) was a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of Tithes, which I took at firſt from your hands as a maintenance allowed me by the Lord, in you and the reſt of the honourable Commiſſioners, who in much love appointed this as a portion for my poor Family, and as a reward for my former ſervices and ſufferings for the State, and the Saints in <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Which undeſerved favour (as I thankfully acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge) ſo did I quietly poſſeſſe the ſame in ſilence and quietneſs of mind, till the Lord God Almighty began to <hi>roar like a man of War,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 42.13, 14</note> 
                     <hi>and to cry like a woman in tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel</hi> within me, bringing forth himſelf in that I ſhall now declare unto you, and to the Churches in <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I told you Sir in private, that in my late publique
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:118421:3"/>Teachings I was carried forth contrary to the inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of my own Spirit, willing rather to ſit ſtill in ſilence, and ſpiritual retirements with my God, wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his glorious appearance with power in all his people.</p>
                  <p>But ſo it was, that by a ſpeciall providence I came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad to the people, whom I acquainted that to my preſent apprehenſion, I was not certain that I had any call from God or man, or from my ſelf, but meerly by a ſtrong hand, I know not how, I was thruſt forth into the Harveſt, where I was immediatly met with the noyſe of Tythes in this manner:</p>
                  <p>The firſt Scripture I opened, not to preach, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to expound, (according to the Teaching of God in mee) was <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 61.1, 2.</p>
                  <p>There I ſaw and ſaid, that God in Chriſt had glad tidings to ſpeak, and great things to doe (in theſe laſt dayes alſo) for three ſorts of people; for the poor, for the oppreſſed, and for the Priſoner.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The meek</hi> thats the <hi>poor,</hi> as Chriſt interprets <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>the broken hearted,</hi> thats the <hi>oppreſſed,</hi> as every Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty can teſtifie, and the <hi>opening of the priſon doors to them that are bound, is good tydings for the Priſoner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This day</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>is this Scripture fulfilled in your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ares;</hi> and this have we heard and ſeen in our dayes, God ſo appearing in the preſent powers, that 'twas hoped this was <hi>the acceptable year of the Lord,</hi> for the people of the Land to look for their long expected and promiſed liberty to the Captives, who, by an Act of Juſtice and Mercy from the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> are ſet free from their ſeverall Priſons, (yea, from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain captivity in part) as the firſt fruits of that follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Redemption which the oppreſſed, and the Poor of the Nation doe likewiſe hope for.</p>
                  <p>But before I heard of that News, I had formed my matter in this Method;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>March</hi> 7.</note> the firſt moneth of the year I began to ſpeak for the poor from theſe Scriptures
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:118421:3"/>on ſeverall Sundayes, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1, 2. and 14.32. <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.12. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.4.</p>
                  <p>With this laſt I began the ſecond moneth for the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72.4.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aprill</hi> 4. <hi>May</hi> 2. to 30</note> (as afterward I ended the third moneth with the Priſoner, from <hi>Iſai.</hi> 42.6, 7, and 49, 8, 9. <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11, 12.) but before that I ſpake for the oppreſſed, from <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. <hi>v.</hi> 1.4. that when <hi>the King and his Son ſhould come to raign, he would break in pieces the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſor,</hi> oppreſſion muſt ceaſe, and the oppreſſed muſt have eaſe.</p>
                  <p>The next firſt day of the week, I ſpake from <hi>v.</hi> 12, 13, 14. That <hi>the bloud</hi> of poor <hi>oppreſſed men is moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious in the eyes of God,</hi> for he <hi>eyes them</hi> and all their op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſors as another Prophet phraſeth it, <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.9.</p>
                  <p>Upon this God began (as I ſaid before) to roar in my Spirit, and I to hear nothing within me but the cry of the oppreſſed, 'twas far (me thought) from my tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to tread on a worm, or to oppreſſe the pooreſt creature in the world, but ſtill 'twas told me both wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and ſleeping that God would <hi>break in pieces the oppreſſor,</hi> and that the <hi>bloud</hi> of the poor was <hi>precious in his ſight.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then the oppreſſion of Tithes came to my eares, and the cry of the oppreſſed filled my heart, telling me, That I and my children fed on their fleſh, that we drunk their bloud, and lived ſoftly on their hard labour and ſweat.</p>
                  <p>All the Petitions againſt Tithes were preſently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and ſpread before me by God, who asked, Is it not the gain of oppreſſion that thou and thine live on?</p>
                  <p>Truly Sir, there was never a day went over my head, but I heard ſomething of him from God, and from men alſo, who, not knowing the working and wrath that was within, did continually hit me in the teeth with ſomething of Tithes.</p>
                  <p>One came to my Chamber, a worthy Gentleman from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:118421:4"/>
                     <hi>England,</hi> complaining of the Commiſſioners of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth</hi>-ſhire, who (as he came along) had a meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Chriſtchurch, to take a more ſtrict account of each mans Tithes, and that he met with many poor country men in the way crying out of their oppreſſion, and that (as they ſaid) by the people of God.</p>
                  <p>Another day an honeſt man of our Country, comes in and tells me, he had formerly taken a good bargain of Tithes from the Commiſſioners or <hi>Glamorgan</hi>-ſhire, but he had no reſt in his ſpirit from the time he farmed it from them, but was continually tormented till he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered it up, which he did (as he ſaid) very quickly, elſe he thought in his heart he had run ſtarke mad out of his wits.</p>
                  <p>And truly Sir 'twas ſo with me in this, though I have been <hi>afflicted from my youth, and ſuffered the terrors of the Lord to diſtraction,</hi> yet (for the time) I was never ſo diſtracted, confounded, and filled with feares in all my former temptations, as in this of Tithes.</p>
                  <p>And yet this trouble was not like thoſe legall terrors I ſuffered of old, but it was like fire in my bones, which I beleeve is the eternall Spirit, and everlaſting burnings, which will ſhortly break forth upon all the oppreſſors of the land, to burn up their fleſh, fulneſſe, and thoſe fair buildings which they have raiſed on the ruines of others, enriching themſelves in the Nations poverty.</p>
                  <p>The fire that was within me had new fuell caſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which to my feeling increaſed to feircer flames, for every day I opened my Bible to read (the remembrance of Tithes coming ſtill to my mind) the firſt line that darted in mine eyes, was alwayes ſomething againſt Oppreſſion, as <hi>Iſay</hi> 5.7, 8. <hi>Micah</hi> 2.2, 3, 8, 9, 10. <hi>ver.</hi> Again, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 9.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 30.10, 11, 12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 22.17. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 7.19. Theſe and many other Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures came not in by way of a Concordance, nor yet as ſought out by me, but they found me out, ſo that I once feared to open the book any more.</p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:118421:4"/>
                  <p>But there <hi>was a book within me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 29.18.</note> which though I would ſhut, and be willingly deaf to what was written therein, yet I was made to hear with a witneſſe, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 33.14. <hi>The ſinners of</hi> Zion <hi>are afraid, fearfulneſſe hath ſurprized the hypocrites, who among us ſhall dwell with the devouring fire? who among us ſhall dwell with the everlaſting burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings? he that walketh righteouſly, and ſpeaketh uprightly, and deſpiſeth the gain of Oppreſſion, &amp;c. he ſhall dwell on high, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This was my morning thought, which made me riſe up quick from my bed,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>April,</hi> 8.</note> and after ſecond thoughts I haſtened away to Church, where the Sheriffe and Judges were expected to come unto ſermon, there I reſolved in the face of all the Country to caſt off the gain of Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, and burthen of Tithes, intending (with their Honours leave) in the end of all, to have ſpoken a few words on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 68.5. But the Judges not coming that day to Church, the Preacher did no more but expound in the pue (there being but a thin Audience) upon this my former reſolutions fell, and I thought within my ſelf, ſurely the Lord would not I ſhould openly meddle with this point, nor be too ſcrupulous in an outward thing, as this of Tithes, ſo I quietly heard the Man, and God alſo, in the very words then read, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 7.7. <hi>Surely Oppreſſion maketh a wiſe man mad, and a gift deſtroyeth the heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For all this I returned home without the leaſt touch, or trouble of conſcience, ſaying, now I ſhall have peace and be ſtill, provided for as formerly, I have been to <hi>offer up my Iſaack,</hi> my beloved Tithes, but the Lord hath ſpared it and accepted me; I ſee <hi>a Ram caught in the buſh for a Sacrifice,</hi> that is, my carnall mind and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination, for now I looked upon this of Tithes but as a fleſhly outward thing, a poor low buſineſs for any ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man to be ſcrupulous of, therefore I ſaid, I would go to my <hi>heights</hi> again, if once I might <hi>ſee the King in his beauty, and the land that is very farre off,</hi> Iſaiah 33.16.17.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:118421:5"/>
                  <p>The next day I came to your chamber, where I was welcomed with reſpect and kindneſſe, but before I could ſleep that night I was awaked again, and the Lord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to <hi>anſwer in the ſecret place of Thunder,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal 81.7.</note> he that <hi>deſpiſeth not the gain of Oppreſſion ſhall not dwell on high.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then down I came to the deep, and dwelt that night in the dark, in the ſhadow of death, yea, in the belly of hell, I cryed the next day alſo, <hi>O Lord I am oppreſſed, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake for me, Iſai.</hi> 38.14.</p>
                  <p>This Scripture was that dayes Text; when I was to ſpeak good things to the oppreſſed, I heard nothing but bad newes and ſad tidings to my ſelf, ſtanding there under the <hi>gain of Oppreſſion,</hi> I could experimentally tell this truth, that God would plague the oppreſſor, in whoſe ſtead (me thought) I was that day <hi>chattering like a Crane, and mourning as a Dove,</hi> in my cry, <hi>O Lord I am oppreſſed, undertake for me,</hi> it was anſwered, thou art an <hi>oppreſſor of men,</hi> and now thou art juſtly oppreſſed by God.</p>
                  <p>That was the ſumme of that morning exerciſe, how men oppreſſe God in mans oppreſſion, and then that God oppreſſeth alſo their ſpirits as they doe his.</p>
                  <p>Truly to that time I never found the experience of this ſo true, <hi>The love of money is the root of all evill,</hi> evill of ſin and of puniſhment, for by this I began, not onely <hi>to erre from the faith,</hi> and from truſting on God, but <hi>to be pierced through with many ſorrowes, yea, to be drowned in perdition and deſtruction,</hi> 1 Tim. 6.9, 10.</p>
                  <p>And yet how often did my deſire to be rich make me fear to be poor, and my proud heart ſeek to ſilence the cries of God and men within me, to ſhift off the thoughts of oppreſſion, and the buſineſſe of Tithes, as a thing not belonging to me, but for the States to reform? Again, my heart told me, that Tithes are now new modled and ſet in another form, with ſome moderation alſo.</p>
                  <p>And again, Tithes are coming into the Treaſury of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:118421:5"/>the Common-wealth, God forbid ſaid one within me, but thought I, why may not I take at preſent this free gift from the civill powers, as the Paſtors, Teachers, and Preachers of the Goſpel in <hi>Wales</hi> this day, who are maintained by Tithes.</p>
                  <p>Oh this renewed my former troubles, enraged thoſe terrors, telling me, if now I be ſilent, I ſhould not onely betray my Country, and the Governours of our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth to the judgement of God, but be baſe, and lye to the Churches, not ſpeaking the truth, which many poor Chriſtians, not attending to, doe daily wound their weak conſciences by a little too much worldli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (as in other things) ſo in farming of Tithes, which all the godly Preachers and people of God in <hi>Wales,</hi> did formerly profeſs, preach, and pray againſt.</p>
                  <p>Thus many Miniſters alſo are unſenſibly fallen into a new light, which themſelves condemned in others, for my part I follow the old, and profeſſe, that I can ſee yet nothing in Tithes but the <hi>gain of Oppreſſion,</hi> continued and kept up meerly by Miniſters, and Church-Members, who being men of power this day, might eaſily prevaile to remove this and many other oppreſſions, at leaſt, with the people of the Land to petition the preſent Governours, to eaſe the oppreſſed of their burthens, as to releaſe the priſoners from their bonds, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive poor families with bread by a publick ſtock.</p>
                  <p>I ſpeak not now of thoſe Tithes which are part of mens temporal eſtates, but of ſuch Eccleſiaſtick revenues appointed at firſt for Popiſh Prieſts, now for Preachers of the Goſpel, this being a greater oppreſſion than the tithes of former times, my ſpirit was oppreſſed by the Lord, till I had quite thrown away this abhomination, and burthen of the Land.</p>
                  <p>Thus then to me it is preſented as more oppreſſive than Prieſtly Tithes; ſecondly, more oppreſſive than Popiſh Tithes; and thirdly, than Prelatick, or Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Tithes heretofore.</p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:118421:6"/>
                  <p>Firſt I ſay, Prieſtly Tithes under the Law had the command of God. Secondly, 'twas not forced on men by the power of the ſword, but either freely given by the people, or urged by the Prophets with promiſes and threats to ſuch who were diſobedient or unwilling: Thirdly,
<note place="margin">Deut. 14.28, 29.</note> the Prieſts did not eat up all the Tithes them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but as there was a yearly Tithe for the Prieſt, ſo every third year, there was a tithe for the poor; Oh, that the poor might have their Arrears out of the unreaſonable gain of Goſpel-Prieſts. Fourthly, Prieſts under the Law had but the tenth, our Preachers of the Goſpel take up the fifth or fourth of mens lands and labours. Fiftly, the Prieſts who had Tithes paid them, had no other portion or temporal eſtate as moſt of our Miniſters have, who may therefore preach the Goſpel freely, if they can.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, they are more oppreſſive than <hi>Popiſh Tithes</hi> in forrain parts, <hi>France,</hi> the Kingdome of Aſſes (as 'tis called) hath not ſuch an oppreſſion in Tithes for their Prieſts, as our Proteſtant Teachers and Preachers of the Goſpel doe burthen this free Nation; for as 'tis cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported by ſome, who have long liv'd in <hi>France,</hi> that there and in <hi>Spain</hi> alſo, onely Tithe of hard corn is paid, that is, of Wheat and Rye, but no Tithe of Barley, Oates, Peaſe, Beans, Fitches, Tills, much leſſe Tithe of Hops, Hemp, Flaxe, Saffron, or of garden Hearbs.</p>
                  <p>Secondly 'tis not the tenth ſheaf as ours, but onely the twentieth ſheaf of Wheat and Rie is paid with them. Thirdly, if there be but nineteen Lambs, there is none, if thirty nine there is but one Lamb for the Prieſt, as one of twentie, and two of fortie is his Tithe, but our Goſpel-Prieſts muſt have one Lamb of ten, yea, one of ſeven if there be no more. Fourthly ours have not onely the tenth Lamb, but tithe of the Wool of the nine remaining, wherers the Popiſh Prieſt hath no tithe of wool at all. Fifthly, They take no Tithe of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:118421:6"/>calves, hay, hay-graſſe, or juſtments, much leſs tithe of pigs, geeſe, apples, eggs, and of every thing almoſt the poor live on our Goſpel Miniſters muſt have their tithes.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly ſince the Independent Paſtors are turnd Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Preachers of the Goſpel, Pariſh Prieſts; the burthen of Tithes hath been more oppreſſive in them, than in the Prelates and Presbyters heretofore. For firſt, Theſe were Nationall Miniſters, and did ſervice to every Pariſh in the Nation, therefore the National maintenance was more of right proper for them, but the Independent Churches, ſeparating from the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and profeſſing a Goſpel-practice, cannot for ſhame deny their own Principles, as to keep up Tithes, but rather to look for a maintenance from their own Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, or to live of the Goſpel, if they preach to the World, I ſay of the Goſpel, that is, to live by faith in God, who will doubtleſſe feed his ſervants, and cauſe men freely to contribute unto them who preach the Goſpel freely. Secondly, The Tithes formerly were never ſo farmed out to Commiſſioners friends, who rackt the poor Pariſhioners to raiſe their own private gain, though they get forty or fiftie ſhillings yearly by the bargain. Thirdly, as 'tis more reaſonable for the Pariſh to farm their own Tithes with the former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batements, ſo in theſe times of publike Taxes, Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions, and neceſſary burthens on the Nation, the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of Tithes is more intollerable, but our Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent friends load the people, who hoped to have been eaſed of all by their meanes. Fourthly, Godly men in <hi>Wales,</hi> who have ſuffred much for the State, and in tenderneſs of conſcience could not pay Tithes to the Prelates of old, yea, who were indulged in thoſe dayes, are now forced not onely to that, but to pay all their Arrears of Tithes formerly ſpared. Fifthly, as Tithes under this oppreſſive Form was firſt eſtabliſhed by the Churches of <hi>Wales,</hi> who have given example for the Engliſh to follow the pattern and oppreſſion; ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:118421:7"/>what the Churches there have gained by this, even more Officers in the Church than ever Chriſt comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as Commiſſioners, Treaſurers, Sequeſtrators and Collectors for Tithes, a thing which neither Law nor Goſpel, nor former Ages ever heard of. Sixt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 6 8, 9.</note> God compareth ſuch unto <hi>Thieves and Robbers: Gilead is a Citie of them that work iniquitie, and polluted with bloud,</hi> or as the Margen reads, <hi>cunning for bloud: And as Troops of Robbers wait for a man, ſo the companie of Prieſts murther in the way by conſent;</hi> the <hi>Geneva</hi> notes <hi>Gilead</hi> to be the Citie where the Prieſts dwelt, and the <hi>companie of them</hi> was like a Synod or Claſſis. Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents and Presbyters agree together and conſent in <hi>Tithes.</hi> Seventhly, Doe not the Churches by this rob God alſo, (this at leaſt being a Typical expreſſion of their ſpiritual robberie) <hi>Will a man rob God? yet yee have robbed me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal. 2.10, 14, 17. Mal. 3.7, 8, 13.</note> 
                     <hi>ſaith the Lord: But ye ſaid, Wherein have we robbed thee? In tithes and offerings,</hi> Mal. 3.8. Pray obſerve in this and in the former Chapters how oft God ſeeks to convince the Prieſts ſix times together, but the Prieſts will by no meanes be convinced by God himſelf of their manifeſt hypocriſie. Secondly, That God ſpeaks to the Prieſts in both Chapters is plain from <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.1. <hi>And now, O ye Prieſts, this word is for you,</hi> and 'tis their word alſo, <hi>Mal</hi> 3.14. <hi>What profit is it that we have kept thy Ordinances, and walked mournfully,</hi> Or as the Hebrew reads it, <hi>walked in black,</hi> that is their garbe, as <hi>Baals Prieſts</hi> are called <hi>Chemarim,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.4.</note> or Black coats: Now, <hi>What profit is it</hi> (ſay they) <hi>that we have kept thine Ordinance?</hi> It is not Ordinances, but thine Ordinance, the Lords Ordinance (as I ſhall ſhew another time) is the Spirits preſence and power from on high, this was the firſt Goſpel-Ordinance, the Baptiſm of the Spirit and of Fire, for the appearance of the Spirit was on every Ordinance of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.4, 5. Acts 2.38. Acts 8.6, 28.</note> in water-Baptiſm, there was the promiſe of the gift of the Spirit, and the power of the Spirit in ſome viſible gifts appeared with every one
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:118421:7"/>that did baptize in breaking of bread,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.13. 1 Cor. 14, 15. 2 Pet. 1.12.</note> they dranke into one Spirit, they did ſing in the Spirit, pray in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, preach the Goſpel with the holy Spirit ſent down from heaven; yea, in truth, all outward Ordinances of the Goſpel were but the Ordinances of man, though appointed by God, the appearance and power of the Spirit was the Ordinance of God, but <hi>what profit</hi> (ſay the Prieſts) <hi>is it that we have kept thine Ordinances,</hi> waited on the Spirit, there's no profit in this.</p>
                  <p>Truly, the Spirits preſence was more waited on, and the Saints in <hi>Wales</hi> were far more ſpiritual before their Church-fellowſhip, more ſimple-hearted, ſincere, ſelf-denying, and dying to the world, yea, though they walkt in Ordinances, there was no talk then of Ordinances, they were dead unto them (it being the worlds Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion) the Saints were all drawn up to the Spirit, which made them to be ſcoft of the world, which now they follow in their principles, practice, and deſire of profit? <hi>What profit ſay they?</hi> Oh, there is no profit in the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits preſence in the Ordinance of God; the power of men, the Ordinance for Tithes, and maintenance for Miniſters hath more profit with it.</p>
                  <p>Well Friends, you muſt ſhortly walk in black, and mournfully with your Forefathers, the Prelates and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, becauſe you follow their ſteps in the height of your Spirits, and lowneſs of your walkings, in your worldly deſigns, in your deſires for profit, your tithes, augmentations, conſolidations, Church offerings and ſuch things, unheard of in Goſpel-times, yea, it was a ſtrange language to latter dayes.</p>
                  <p>But how doe the Prieſts <hi>rob God in tithes and offerings?</hi> the people rather ſhould be ſaid to rob the Prieſts in this, and yet it is proved before that all was ſpoken of the Prieſts, <hi>they rob God in Tithes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly there's a Myſtery in this (as in all other legall expreſſions (<hi>Mal.</hi> 1.11. <hi>Iſai.</hi> 66.23.) For as Gods <hi>Tith or tenth</hi> is that ſmall remnant of his people
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:118421:8"/>reſerved from the Churches Apoſtaſie, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 6.13. <hi>In it ſhall be the tenth,</hi> &amp;c. So the <hi>Lords offerings</hi> is all the <hi>people of the land: Bring yee all the Tithes into my ſtorehouſe that there may be meat in mine houſe, Mal.</hi> 3.10. The Lords Houſe is of a larger building then the gathered Churches have ſet up, as you may ſee <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 66.19, 20. Where many Nations, yea, ſtrange and ſavage people are brought into the houſe of God, who (I beleive) in his due time will gather theſe three Nations into one Church, (as the firſt fruits of his glory and fame to the world)</p>
                  <p>So then the <hi>whole Nation</hi> is the <hi>Lords offering,</hi> a Nation to be offred unto God. God is now rob'd of this offering by our Goſpel-Prieſts, not onely the Tithes, the ſcattered Saints, but the Nation, even the Lords offering God is robbed of by the gathered Churches and their Prieſts.</p>
                  <p>For ſo it is clearer expreſt by <hi>Malachy,</hi> c. 3. v. 9. <hi>Ye are curſed with a curſe, for yee have robbed me, even this whole Nation,</hi> not that the whole Nation did rob God, as the words ſeem to import, but taking away the word [even] not in the Hebrew, the ſence is clear, <hi>ye have robbed me this whole Nation;</hi> that is, as <hi>[God with us]</hi> is the Nations Motto, ſo God in the Nation, or the whole Nation, as the offering or people of God, the Independent Churches will not own, though the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters in this are of a better judgement, who profeſſe the Nation to be in Covenant with God, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and upon this account baptize all their children, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But ſure 'tis a truth not onely in the Myſterie, but in the Hiſtorie or Letter, The Prieſts in Tithes and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings doe <hi>rob the whole Nation,</hi> for the Nation is even ruined by the oppreſſion thereof, Therefore our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-Prieſts, who by the power of the ſword take up their Tithes, or other wayes force a maintenance from the people, are called thieves and robbers by God.</p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:118421:8"/>
                  <p>Oh how ſecretly and ſuddenly is the day of the Lord, or the Lords day ſtollen upon the Churches of <hi>Wales,</hi> Chriſt being come as a Theif in the night to ſpoil them of all their glory and honour, yea, their goodneſs is quite gone, and carried away into captivity.</p>
                  <p>For how hath <hi>God prophaned the Princes of the Sanctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> or <hi>the holy Princes,</hi> as the Hebrew reads.
<note place="margin">Iſai. 43.28.</note> The <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Princes</hi> in Church and Commonwealth are not onely become <hi>prophane,</hi> covetous, cruel, cunning for bloud, but they are prophaned by God, this the <hi>holy Princes</hi> will not hear that God ſhould prophane any man, but now they may learn by experience, and be made to cry at laſt; <hi>Lord, why haſt thou made us to erre from thy wayes, and hardned our hearts from thy fear,?</hi> Iſai. 63.17.</p>
                  <p>Oh what prophaneſſe is this, that the holy Princes ſhould be not onely proud, peeviſh, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but thieves and robbers in the way, to rob the whole Nation,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 43.28.</note> to rob God and man at once?</p>
                  <p>No wonder, <hi>God doth give Jacob to the curſe, and Iſrael to reproaches:</hi> This is worſe then hanging it ſelf to have the curſe of God, and the contempt of man; truly it is far from my temper to reproach any man, much leſſe the people of God, but if God ſhall give them to the reproach and the curſe, what man can help it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I will ſend a curſe upon you, and curſe your bleſſings, yea, I have curſed them already, becauſe ye have not laid it to heart,</hi> Mal. 2.2. <hi>Behold I will corrupt your ſeed,</hi> (or as the Margent reads, <hi>I will reprove your ſeed,</hi> and not onely the Word you preach, but the tithe-corn you gather for pay, and the tithe of your cattle too, <hi>I will ſpread their dung on your faces, and the dung of your ſolemn feaſts, and thanksgiving dayes,</hi> when ye look up to bleſs my Name, <hi>I will ſpread dung on your faces,</hi> v. 3.</p>
                  <p>And then it followes <hi>one ſhall take you away with it, v.</hi> 3. One, Who is that? Sure there needs not the ſtrength of many, but <hi>one</hi> man, yea, a babe in Chriſt can take away the Church with the Prieſt from their ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:118421:9"/>places. How eaſie is it for <hi>one,</hi> for a very child, with his little finger to puſh down all the Churches in <hi>Wales,</hi> being fallen already by their own diviſions and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in worſhip, and in their walkings alſo, their wrath, worldlineſs, and which is worſe, the thing of Tithes, wherewith they have foul'd their fingers.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Yee are departed out of the way, yee have cauſed many to ſtumble at the Law, (or in the Law) yee have corrupted the covenant of</hi> Levi, <hi>v.</hi> 8. Whats the Covenant of <hi>Levi?</hi> Oh to live in the Lord alone, to look for maintenance from him onely, no other maintenance but himſelf, for he was <hi>Levies</hi> portion.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was with <hi>Levi,</hi> and the Prieſts of old under the Law, the other Tribes had portions in the land, but the Lord God alone was <hi>Levies</hi> portion, and yet his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance was from all, ſo <hi>Levi</hi> wanted nothing, though he had no portion but the Lord. Thus 'twas with the Apoſtles and Primitive preachers of the Goſpel,
<note place="margin">Luke 22.35.</note> they went forth <hi>without ſcrip or ſilver in their purſes,</hi> yet they <hi>wanted nothing,</hi> and having <hi>nothing, they poſſeſſed all things,</hi> 2 Cor. 6.10.</p>
                  <p>But our Goſpel-Prieſts muſt have portions in the Land,
<note place="margin">Mal. 2.9.</note> or pay in their hand, elſe they will not preach: Therefore ſaith God, <hi>I have made you contemptible and baſe before all the people.</hi> Truly Sir, as I was forcibly carried forth to ſpeak at firſt, ſo now to write my laſt, which I pray receive as the words of a dying man, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring to dye to all things below God to my own life and livelihood.</p>
                  <p>Others preach for a hundred pound a year, I have now preached to loſe it, in which indeed I have found my life, and a better livelihood in the Lord, who hath promiſed that he will not <hi>leave me, nor forſake me,</hi> Hebr. 13. And truly you may beleeve me, I have more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, quietneſſe, comfort in my preſent loſſe, and low eſtate,
<note place="margin">Mich. 5.7.</note> then in all my gainfull Tithes.</p>
                  <p>I then laboured to be rich, I now learn to bee poor,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:118421:9"/>to be Independent indeed, to <hi>depend on no man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Micah 5.7.</note> 
                     <hi>not to wait on men, nor the ſounes of men,</hi> but on the mercifull providence and diſpoſe of God for my abode and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus ſaith the Lord God,
<note place="margin">Jer. 49.11.</note> 
                     <hi>Leave thy fatherleſſe children, and I will preſerve them alive, and let thy widdows truſt in me,</hi> my children are now fatherleſſe, and my wife a widdow, but God will be a father to them and a husband to her, yea, her Phyſitian alſo according to promiſe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.6, 7, 8. But all men are my fleſh alſo, and becauſe I would not <hi>hide my ſelf</hi> from them,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 58.7.</note> I had it once in my thoughts to take this hundred pound at preſent, and to give it as a publike ſtock for the poor of <hi>Cardiffe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It was preſently anſwered unto me,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 61.8.</note> 
                     <hi>I hate robbery for burnt offerings,</hi> &amp;c. God will ſhortly provide for the poor, though Man will not: Yea, men ſhall at laſt, whether they will or no, when God ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear in them as fire to burn up all their fulneſſe, when <hi>the ruſt of their ſilver ſhall eat up their fleſh as fire,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iames 5.3. Iſai. 2.20.</note> when they ſhall <hi>caſt their Idols of ſilver and gold to the Moles and the Batts,</hi> who lye now in the duſt, and flie in the dark. Laſtly, In the day of wrath,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.19.</note> when they ſhall caſt their ſilver in the Streets, then God will find a way to feed the <hi>poor out of the bellies of the rich,</hi> who ſhall not onely make reſtitution accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their ſubſtance, but ſhall vomit up all that they have ſwallowed, yea, it is a wonder, <hi>their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren ſhall ſeek to pleaſe the poor,</hi> and reſtore all their goods, <hi>Job</hi> 20.10, 15, 18. compared; I am waiting for the fulfilling of his Word, which God will haſten this in his due time, in mean while, I can but pitie the poor, and the rich alſo, even the great Oppreſſor, whoſe plague is coming, I have no more to ſay, but to aſſure you that I am in truth:</p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Sir,</salute> 
                     <signed>Your much ingaged Friend and Servant in the Lord, <hi>WILLIAM ERBERIE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118421:10"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:118421:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>THE Sword Doubled To cut off both the RIGHTEOUS AND THE WICKED;</p>
                  <p>Drawn forth in two following Diſcourſes, By WILLIAM ERBERIE.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>ISAIA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 31.4.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Thus hath the Lord ſpoken unto me, like as the Lyon and the young Lion roaring on his prey, when a multitude of Shepherds is called forth againſt him, he will not be afraid of their voyce, nor abaſe himſelf for the noiſe of them; So ſhall the Lord of Hoſts come down to fight for mount Zion, and for the bill-thereof.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. D.</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Sign of the Black Spread-Eagle at the Weſt End of <hi>Pauls,</hi> 1652.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:118421:11"/>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:118421:11"/>
                  <head>To the Independent Paſtors and Teachers in <hi>Wales,</hi> and in <hi>England</hi> alſo.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great deſign that <hi>God hath to doe</hi> this day is to <hi>undoe man,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. 3.19. Hag. 2.22.</note> and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ones of the earth <hi>by dividing and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying</hi> that oppreſſive power upon the <hi>ſtates and ſpirits of men,</hi> that the <hi>outward and inward man</hi> may have deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance at laſt, and perfect liberty to <hi>ſerve the Lord in holineſs and righteouſneſs before him without fear all the dayes of our life.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 1.75.</note> This was the end of <hi>Chriſts firſt coming in the fleſh,</hi> and of his ſecond <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> by which as <hi>the man of ſin,</hi> the <hi>great whore Babylon</hi> muſt be deſtroyed: ſo divided <hi>into three parts,</hi> as in the ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Midian,</hi> by the <hi>annointing</hi> by the Spirit of the Lord, or God manifeſt in our fleſh, by whom all <hi>yokes</hi> and burthens are removed, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 10.26, 27.</p>
                  <p>Now <hi>Babylon</hi> or the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> being the <hi>great Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor</hi> in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common wealth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 17.3.</note> in the <hi>Civill</hi> and <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick eſtate</hi> (for the <hi>Beaſt</hi> carries the <hi>Whore</hi>) both muſt be broken, as all the Prophets, and <hi>John</hi> the laſt doth propheſie: <hi>Babylon is fallen, is fallen,</hi> and a third fall wee ſhall ſee anon. <hi>How hath the Oppreſſer fallen,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſaiah 14.4.</note> 
                     <hi>the golden citie, the Lord hath broken the ſtaffe of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked, and the rod of the Rulers:</hi> The rod of Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appears not to men, but in the civil eſtate, and the ſtaffe of the wicked there, but we ſhall find it more in the rulers or ruling Elders of Churches, we lookt for
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:118421:12"/>the wicked onely in the world,
<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.10, 11</note> but ſince the rod is bud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, pride hath bloſſomed, and <hi>wickedneſſe is grown up co a rod;</hi> the wicked may be found in the Church, in <hi>Iſrael</hi> it ſelf: The Church I call now the people of God, in Church fellowſhip or not; but as <hi>among my people, ſaith God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 5.26.</note> 
                     <hi>are found wicked men, who ſurpaſſe the deeds</hi> of the wicked: ſo ſince God hath <hi>prophaned the Princes of the Sanctuary,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſal. 43.26.</note> 
                     <hi>or the holy Princes,</hi> as I ſaid before; there are principall men among the people of God, for whom the Prophet muſt cry and howle, becauſe <hi>the Sword is drawn forth both againſt the righteous and the wicked,</hi> Ezek. 21 3. And <hi>againſt all the Princes of Iſrael,</hi> verſe 12. Yea, the Sword is doubled the third time, the <hi>Sword of the great men, which enters into their privy Chambers,</hi> (or cloſeſt Councels) <hi>and the point of the Sword is ſet againſt their gates,</hi> (or Governments) that <hi>their hearts may faint, and their ruines be multiplied, ah it is made bright, and wrapt for ſlaughter,</hi> verſe 14, 15.</p>
                  <p>But among <hi>all the holy Princes</hi> there is one eſpecially whom the Lord calls upon, <hi>Thou prophane wicked Prince, whoſe day is come, when iniquity ſhall have an end,</hi> verſe 25. <hi>Remove the Diadem, take off the Crown, this ſhall not be the ſame, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As King and Lords had an end, and twice the Sword hath been againſt the <hi>Prclatick</hi> and <hi>Presbyterian</hi> party, ſo the Sword being doubled, <hi>the third time will ſmite that prophane and wicked Prince,</hi> whatever he be, who is the Oppreſſor, who is <hi>imperious, proud, peeviſh, covetous, cruell and cunning</hi> for bloud; oh the Sword of the Lord will find him out, for 'tis <hi>wrapt for ſlaughter,</hi> 'tis wrapt, I ſay, and <hi>ſecretly 'twill come forth,</hi> to cut off the man that ſtands before God, to oppoſe <hi>the appearance of God in men,</hi> to oppreſſe the ſpirits of men, and the Spirit of God in them, <hi>the Sword of his mouth ſhall ſlay him,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8.</p>
                  <p>I ſhall not now meddle with matters of State, nor of ſecular men (though theſe alſo may come under the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:118421:12"/>King of <hi>Babylon</hi>) but our Lords ſpirituall are thoſe here who are called <hi>the King of</hi> Babylon, <hi>againſt whom thou ſhalt take up a Proverb or a taunt, ſaying, How hath the Oppreſſor ceaſed? The golden City</hi> ceaſed, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 14.4.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The golden City</hi> is the moſt glorious Church ſtate, or the people of God in higheſt honour and glory; this <hi>is the golden City,</hi> or (as the <hi>Geneva</hi> reads) the <hi>Gold thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting City, the exactreſſe of Gold,</hi> as the margin notes.</p>
                  <p>None doe more exact, and more thirſt after Silver and Gold this day, then <hi>the people of God in ſpirituall power,</hi> and therefore no wonder they doe ſo oppreſſe both the ſtates of men, and the ſpirits of men, yea, the Spirit of God, as may be ſeen at large, <hi>Micah</hi> 2.2, 6, 7. compared with 8, 9, 10. verſes, <hi>Even of late my people is riſen up as an Enemy, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Oh the great Oppreſſor! how the earth doth rejoyce at the ruine of that man, <hi>who ſmote the peogle in wrath</hi> with a <hi>continuall ſtroke, that ruled the Nations in anger,</hi> (no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of love, mercy, and goodneſſe to mankind, or the poor, appeared in him) <hi>but he perſecuteth and no man hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 14.6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <p>And as the <hi>whole Earth is merry at his fall,</hi> ſo <hi>hell from beneath is moved for him, to meet him at his coming it ſtirs up, the dead, even all the cheif ones of the earth, and all the Kings of the Nations riſe up from their Thrones, they ſay, art thou alſo weak as we? art thou become like unto us?</hi> verſe 4.10.</p>
                  <p>What are the <hi>people of God,</hi> and <hi>Princes of Iſrael the holy Princes, ſo prophane?</hi> Is the <hi>prophane Prince of Iſrael ſo weak?</hi> weak as the imperious whoriſh woman? <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.30. Art thou ſo weak as we? weak in thy paſſions and pettiſh Spirit? art thou become like unto us, as one of the Kings of <hi>England,</hi> or the Princes of <hi>Wales?</hi> What man would think, that the Church or People of God ſhould ever come to this, to oppreſſe both God and man, good and bad at once? But this is naturall to ſpirituall men in Church formes, yea, to the fleſh of the beſt
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:118421:13"/>Chriſtians,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.3. Gal. 4.29.</note> who may for a time be very fleſhly, and yet the children of God, as <hi>Iſhmael was Abrahams ſonne after the fleſh, perſecuting him that was born after the Spirit;</hi> yea, Saints by calling may be called carnall, much more <hi>when they are become ſo wiſe after the fleſh, ſo mighty, and ſo noble,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.26.</note> which muſt have an Almighty power of the Spirit, to make them fooliſh, and weak, and baſe, and nothing, to bring to nought things that are; the great things and Conqueſts here attained by the people of God was when they were nothing, now being ſomething they are overcome by all, and by themſelves.</p>
                  <p>When men doe adore the people of God, and idolize them as <hi>the Gods of the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zeph. 2.11.</note> then a thouſand to one, <hi>God does befoole and famiſh them,</hi> and they fall to be proud, and to oppreſs the world, yea, their own Brethren, and their Father alſo, even the moſt high God, appearing in loweſt Saints above them in grace, and the knowledge of our Lord, in ſimplicity, in pureneſſe, and peace, and in patience alſo.</p>
                  <p>Well this is the thing that God will <hi>doe with his own,</hi> he will <hi>undoe them,</hi> either by the high diſcoveries of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in them, as the Prophet was, <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 6.1. who came to this, that he ſaw himſelf, though as good as the beſt, yet as bad as the worſt, <hi>verſe</hi> 3, 5. Or elſe he will undoe them, by diſcovering that without to the world which is within in the heart,
<note place="margin">1 King. 8.38. Iam. 3.6.</note> what <hi>a plague is</hi> in it? <hi>what a ſinke and ſea of ſin?</hi> yea, a hell is in the tongue, this the Saints will not ſee, but God does, and men ſhall, when he ſhall turn their inſide out, their hidden hypocriſie ſhall appear to all, for they ſhall openly <hi>practiſe hypocriſie,</hi> as men doe groſſe prophaneneſs, for <hi>the vile perſon ſhall be no more called liberall, nor the Churle ſaid to be bountifull, &amp;c.</hi> Iſaiah 32.5, 6, 7. ſee it.</p>
                  <p>Alas man, <hi>Thou maiſt give all that thou haſt to the poor yet have no love:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 13.3. Tit. 3.4. 1 Ioh. 4.16.</note> Oh belye not the Spirit of God in thee, for <hi>God is love, and good to all mankind,</hi> while thou art a <hi>murtherer</hi> in hating <hi>thy brother, John</hi> 3.15. yea, in not
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:118421:13"/>loving him ſo as to <hi>lay down thy life for him,</hi> verſe 16. much more in not laying out thy livelihood, and <hi>this worlds good,</hi> verſe 17. not onely for the godly, as they ſay, but for any man that needs thee, who is both thy brother and <hi>thine own fleſh,</hi> Iſaiah 58.7.</p>
                  <p>Nay tis not enough that thou art no Oppreſſor, as I ſaid before, but <hi>to looſe the bands of wickedneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 58.6.</note> 
                     <hi>to undoe the heavy burthens, to let the Oppreſſed goe free, and to break every yoak is the duty of love, if there be power in thine bands to doe it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when the people of God are ſilent, and ſit ſtill, ſeeking onely ſelf, not ſenſible of the <hi>burthens of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed,</hi> of the <hi>Priſoners bands,</hi> nor of <hi>poor families who cry for bread,</hi> how dwelleth the love of God in them, ſaith <hi>John.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well, want of love, beſides worldlineſſe, wrath, and that oppreſſive power in the Churches,
<note place="margin">Gen. 49.7. Iſai. 19.2. Ier. 51 49.</note> is the cauſe why they are ſo divided among themſelves, yea, <hi>God divides them</hi> (as he did <hi>prophane them) he ſets Brother againſt Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Ruler againſt Ruler, one ruling Elder againſt another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>'Tis Rule and Government the Churches ſtill aime at, therefore they not onely daſh one againſt another, but are like to deſtroy that civill Government, and the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours they depend upon, for ſince the Apoſtacy, the Churches have ever had a dependance on worldly powers, and undone the powers with themſelves, and therefore our preſent Governours are wiſe to beware of men.</p>
                  <p>But Men, and Miniſters, and Churches, as we ſee, are divided this day like <hi>Babylon</hi> into three parts, as we ſhall ſhew anon, and ſo their deſtruction is of themſelves; I ſay, they ſeek for rule, and this ruines them.</p>
                  <p>Now there is a threefold kind of Government among men <hi>Monarchy, Ariſtocracy,</hi> and <hi>Democracy;</hi> the firſt is as of the King, the ſecond is like that of the Parliament, the preſent Government ſome compare to the third, though it appears not yet, but Parliament and Army have voted
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:118421:14"/>the Supream power to be in the people.</p>
                  <p>Well, the Churches muſt have power and rule alſo, the Prelatick Church was <hi>Monarchicall,</hi> all were ruled by one, by an Arch-Biſhop, the Kingly Power or Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative fell by that: The Presbyterian Church is an <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> the Elders or chief of theſe govern as 'twere in a Parliament, and Parliamentary priviledges was like to fall by them, if not fallen already: The Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, or baptized Churches (both is one) are a pure <hi>Democracy,</hi> for not the ruling men, or Miniſters, but all the Members, have equall power to order and ordain as they profeſſe, and therefore called Independent, I wiſh they were ſo, but if they have a dependance on the Civill or Martiall power, 'twill be worſe for both, if both be not wiſer than former times.</p>
                  <p>A word to the wiſe, 'tis my folly to uſe ſo many to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding men as the Miniſters are, eſpeciall Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, being men of parts, power, policy, and of piety al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo many; I ſhall fear none of them, becauſe I love them all, and they me, though wrath at preſent may appear in both, as it doth among themſelves ('twas ſo once be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God and his own people of old, a perfect-hatred, <hi>loathing and abhorring one another.</hi>)</p>
                  <p>Well, the Vials are yet full of the wrath of God, when theſe are poured forth, Love will appear, that is, the Lord himſelf in us all, who will bring forth light out of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and love out of our diviſions: And as he <hi>in wrath remembers mercy,</hi> ſo in much love, I pray you, remember</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your, <hi>WILLIAM ERBERIE.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:118421:14"/>
                  <head>A Scourge for the Aſſyrian, the great OPPRESSOR:</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>ZACH 11.8.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>Three Shepherds I cut off in one moneth, my ſoul loathed them, and their ſoul abhorred me: <hi>That is, the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Appearance of the great God in men, is moſt abhorred by ſeeming godly men, and Miniſters, or</hi> three Shepherds, <hi>whom God therefore loathes, and hates all</hi> their performances, as they hate his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance; <hi>the hatred of both is perfect,</hi> for his ſoul loathes them, and their ſoul abhorreth him.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S Chriſt is the <hi>glory of the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 1.1.3. Iohn 14.10. Ioh. 15.23, 24 Iſai. 8.18. Hebr. 2.12, 13 compared.</note> the appearance of God, or <hi>God manifeſt in fleſh;</hi> ſo <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the <hi>Father in him,</hi> was that which was moſt hated by the <hi>Church of the Jews,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt in us;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 14.11 Eph. 5.30. Heb. 2.11. compared.</note> Chriſt in the Church is abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the <hi>Chriſtian Churches;</hi> who not knowing the <hi>Deity</hi> nor the <hi>humanity</hi> of Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, will not acknowledge the <hi>Father</hi> to be the <hi>God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head of Chriſt,</hi> nor his <hi>brethren to be his humanitie,</hi> in whom the fulneſſe of the Godhead is ſo embodyed,
<note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.12. Eph. 4.13. compared.</note> that he being the <hi>head,</hi> and they the <hi>members,</hi> they and he make <hi>one perfect man,</hi> in whom God appears to be <hi>all in all,</hi> 1 Cor. 15.28.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>Myſterie of God, even the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col 2.2.</note> 
                     <hi>and of Chriſt</hi> is
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:118421:15"/>therefore abhorred by the <hi>ſhepherds,</hi> or Paſtors of Churches,
<note place="margin">Gal. 1.16. Eph. 1.17. Col. 1.27. compared.</note> becauſe they knew not the <hi>Father</hi> in the Son, nor the <hi>Son</hi> in the Saints, nor the <hi>Spirit</hi> in both, which would reveal <hi>this glory in them,</hi> God in their Fleſh, that is <hi>Chriſt in us the hope of glory,</hi> which now they <hi>hate and abher,</hi> not having higher diſcoveries of God, then what they have read in traditional forms of <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine received,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 2.8.</note>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17. 1 Ioh. 1.1. Rom. 9 1. Heb. 1.3.8. Col. 1.15.13 Col. 2.9. compared.</note> 
                     <hi>and invented by men.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For as the Father is <hi>the inviſible God</hi> inhabiting eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, ſo Chriſt is <hi>God viſible,</hi> the Image or out-goings of God, the glory of the Father (in fleſh) the appearance of God, (as I ſaid) or <hi>God manifeſt in fleſh,</hi> who in the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit was from the beginning, and will be to the end, though this <hi>myſtery of Chriſt</hi> was not manifeſted to men till the <hi>fulneſs of time,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 9, 6. Ioh. 5.19, 20, 30. Iohn 8.28. Iohn 14.10 compared. 2 Cor. 13.4. 1 Pet. 1.21. Pſal. 68.1. Pſal. 68.18. Eph. 4.10. Ioh. 16.28. Iohn 17.8.</note> when the <hi>mighty God, the everlaſting Father</hi> appeared in fleſh, taken of a Virgin, then the <hi>Son was born,</hi> for God was brought forth in fleſh, and was manifeſt in fleſh <hi>by mighty works and words which he ſpake and did,</hi> while he lived in the dayes of his fleſh, but in his death, <hi>God crucified that fleſh to himſelf,</hi> which af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward <hi>he raiſed to glory, God riſing</hi> or revealing himſelf gloriouſly therein, then God <hi>aſcended up on high,</hi> that is, <hi>God in fleſh</hi> did aſcend not onely to <hi>heaven,</hi> but far <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all heavens,</hi> into his own <hi>eternall abiſſe, and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible being, and unacceſſible light,</hi> whence the <hi>bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his glory proceeded,</hi> and came <hi>forth in fleſh</hi> in the fulneſs of time, as we ſaid before.</p>
                  <p>But this Myſterie was not <hi>made known nor manfeſted</hi> to the <hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>men,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 3.5.</note> till God who <hi>aſcended up in fleſh,</hi> ſent down the <hi>Spirit from on high,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 68.18. Eph. 4.8.</note> when he not onely <hi>recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved gifts for men,</hi> or as Hebrew reads, <hi>received gifts in the man, but gave gifts unto men;</hi> that is, the ſame Spirit and power of God, dwelling in the fleſh of Chriſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in the Church which is called Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. becauſe the <hi>Son</hi> was <hi>revealed,</hi> or known in the Saints, and they in the <hi>Son,</hi> and <hi>both in the Father,</hi> all perfect in one; for which cauſe the Spirit is called the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:118421:15"/>
                     <hi>promiſe of the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 1.4. Rom. 8.25.17</note> and the <hi>Spirit of the Son</hi> in the Saints <hi>cryed, Abba Father,</hi> God being a Father to them as to him, his God and theirs. For though the Spirit be called the Spirit of the Son, yet he received and ſent it from the Father, therefore the Spirit is ſaid to <hi>proceed</hi> onely from the <hi>Father,</hi> &amp;c. it is the <hi>promiſe of the Father,</hi> the power of God from on high, which the Saints received from and with the Son, they being Sons and coheirs with him, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.26. This Myſtery of Chriſt though once <hi>manifeſted to the Apoſtles and Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Saints by the Spirit,</hi> and ſince ſhut up as a <hi>ſealed book</hi> by the apoſtaſie or ſpirit of Antichriſt in the Churches, yet the <hi>book will be open, the myſtery will be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt again, for the myſtery of God ſhall be finiſhed,</hi> and fully known at laſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.7.
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.4. Rev. 2.8.</note> But as Chriſt is <hi>the firſt</hi> and <hi>the laſt,</hi> he who <hi>was, is, and is to come,</hi> of Chriſt <hi>was</hi> vayled in the Law, and <hi>is</hi> revelaed in the Goſpel, (though but in part) the full Revelation of Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus is <hi>to come,</hi> Jeſus Chriſt the <hi>ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever,</hi> not Chriſt after the fleſh, for that was not till <hi>the fulneſs of time,</hi> but Chriſt in the Spirit,
<note place="margin">Heb. 13.8.</note> 
                     <hi>God manifeſt in fleſh,</hi> was both <hi>yeſterday</hi> under the Law, and in the <hi>day</hi> of Goſpel-diſpenſation, and in the third diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation now approaching, he will abide <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>There was a change indeed from Law to Goſpel, when the Spirit of Chriſt firſt came into the Church; the ſtate of the Goſpel changed alſo, when the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt</hi> came in power, and the Churches fell by the Apoſtaſie; when Chriſt ſhall come the ſecond time <hi>in ſpirit and glory, time ſhall be no more,</hi> no more change of things ſhall be, for <hi>all things and times ſhall appear in eternity,</hi> which is the third diſpenſation, as the firſt was <hi>yeſterday,</hi> the ſecond to <hi>day,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 10 6, 7.</note> ſo the third is to be <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall not now ſpeak at large of this third <hi>diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> onely as <hi>God is both Father, Son, and Spirit;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.7.</note> So God being manfeſt to his people in this threefold diſcovery
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:118421:16"/>of himſelf, declares the <hi>third diſpenſation,</hi> a third diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of himſelf unto them, and in them.</p>
                  <p>God <hi>under the Law</hi> and to the Fathers before was known as <hi>the Father.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6. Rom. 1.9. Rev. 22.17.</note> In <hi>the Goſpel</hi> God was known, as <hi>the ſon,</hi> or the knowledge of the Son was peculiar to the Goſpel-diſpenſation. The third will be <hi>pure Spirit,</hi> when nothing but Spirit and power ſhall appear, when God ſhall be all in all: For although Goſpel-believers were baptized into the name of Father, Son and Spirit, yet what they poſſeſſed was but <hi>the firſt fruits of the Spirit,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.23.</note> there will be a full harveſt, flouds, and <hi>Rivers of waters of life which no man can paſſe over,</hi> when the <hi>earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord</hi> (or as another Prophet adds) <hi>full of the knowledge of the glory of the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 47.5. Iſai. 11.9. Hab. 1.14. Zach. 14.8. Rev. 22.1. compared.</note> 
                     <hi>as the waters cover the Sea,</hi> Iſai. 11.9. <hi>Hab.</hi> 2.14. There the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb, God even the Father, and Chriſt the Fathers glory ſhall be fully known by men;
<note place="margin">Rev. 21.22. Rev. 22.4.</note> For as <hi>Chriſt is the appearance of God,</hi> ſo when <hi>God ſhall appear in men</hi> they ſhall know how Chriſt <hi>was</hi> under the Law, and as he <hi>is</hi> in the Goſpel, and will be the ſame <hi>for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>All that I know at preſent of Chriſt is this, he was under the Law in <hi>Forms:</hi> In the Goſpel hee appeared in <hi>Fleſh;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tit. 2.13. Heb. 9.28.</note> he will appear wholly <hi>in Spirit,</hi> in Spirit one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>appecarance of the great GOD and Saviour ſhall be,</hi> and yet <hi>manifeſt in the fleſh of men,</hi> that is, all the tranſactions of God, or all that God did in the fleſh of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Rev. 12.5. Rev. 11.8, 11, 12. 1 Cor. 6.2, 3. Obad. 21. compared.</note> ſhall viſibly appear in the fleſh of men; the birth of Chriſt, his life, death, reſurrection, and aſcention ſhall be ſeen in us, men ſhall ſee us <hi>aſcend in a cloud,</hi> to ſit in heaven to <hi>judge the world and Angels,</hi> and to bee <hi>Saviours of men in mount Zion at laſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Lamb ſhall bee in mount Zion, and with him we ſhall be,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 14.1.</note> 
                     <hi>having his Fathers name on our foreheads,</hi> that's the full diſcovery of God in us, and men ſhall ſee God, even the Father in us with Chriſt, ſo cleerly manifeſt as <hi>written on our foreheads.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:118421:16"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mount Sion</hi> is not an outward Church-ſtate, as the Churches now imagine, and call themſelves, though they be indeed the <hi>daughter of Babylon;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 2.7.</note> but <hi>Zion is</hi> the <hi>ſtate of all the Saints in the Spirit as they are in God, and God in them:</hi> For as <hi>Zion</hi> was the place where God dwelt; ſo all the Saints from the beginning of the world have been ſtill waiting for this, for the full diſcoverie of God in them. <hi>Glorious things were ſpoken of Zion,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 87.3.</note> and the people of God both under the law, and in Goſpel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpenſation were ſtill going on <hi>from ſtrength to ſtrength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 84.7.</note> 
                     <hi>till every one of them appears in Zion before God.</hi> Every one appears at laſt in Zion, <hi>Rev,</hi> 14.1. not onely the <hi>hundred and fourſcore and four thouſand,</hi> who go before, and are the firſt fruits unto God, <hi>v.</hi> 4. but a number<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs company of men, (<hi>whoſe voyce was as many waters, and as a mighty thunder,</hi> verſ. 2. For as the hundred fourſcore and four thouſand is the juſt number of the ſealed ones. <hi>Rev.</hi> 7 4. ſelected out of the twelve Tribes, who were firſt called the <hi>Church and people of God,</hi> typi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying thoſe in the laſt dayes who ſhall be <hi>redeemed from men, and the firſt fruits unto God,</hi> as we ſaid before; ſo afterward there will be a company of people called to God whom no man can number, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7.9. But theſe come to <hi>Zion through great tribulation, through the bloud of the Lamb in them,</hi> v. 14. that is, through much ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, through the <hi>fellowſhip of Chriſts ſuffering, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to his death</hi> they come to riſe, and raign with him, having <hi>palms in their hauds;</hi> that life of Goſpel-Saints which was <hi>hid with Chriſt in God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Col. 3.3.</note> ſhall appear in God, and the life of God ſhall appear in the Saints at laſt, thus Chriſt <hi>their life ſhall appear in them with glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This glorious appearing of the great God, riſing up in higher diſcoveries of himſelf in men, is that which hath been ever moſt oppoſed and perſecuted; I ſpeak not now of the times under the Law, nor Goſpel, nor yet of former appearances, ſince the Apoſtaſie. But
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:118421:17"/>to goe no further then our own age, what we have heard and ſeen: How was the appearance of God in the Firſt Reformers, yea, in our Prelates and Biſhops per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted as hereſie by the Popiſh Hierarchie! Next the honeſt Presbyters or Puritans how were they oppoſed by the ſame Prelates, who ſuffered before? Thirdly, theſe Presbyterians formerly themſelves in a ſuffering condition, perſecuted the appearance of God in thoſe of higher forms and fellowſhips, as the Independent Churches; and theſe likewiſe are ready to oppoſe and perſecute the ſpirits of the Saints, who in worſhip and doctrine are of higher diſcoveries then themſelves.</p>
                  <p>The doctrine of <hi>God and of Chriſt</hi> for ſubſtance is the ſame in all the Saints, though their apprehenſions dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, or are divers rather. And who is ignorant of this, that the appearances of God in one man, hath not been the ſame as it was formerly in himſelf? and yet all have been going on from <hi>ſtrength to ſtrength,</hi> at leaſt in their deſires and aimes toward Zion.</p>
                  <p>Though I am but a child in underdanding, and in yeares alſo to ſome of our Elders, yet here I obſerved four great ſteps of Gods glorious appearance in mens preaching.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, how low and legall were their teachings, as they learnt the way of preaching from Mr. <hi>Perkins, Bolton, Byfield, Dod,</hi> and <hi>Dike,</hi> moſt bleſſed in their ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, by whom, and ſuch conforming Miniſters, more men were converted to God, then ever ſince in any period of time.</p>
                  <p>Next the Doctrine of free Grace came forth, but with leſſe ſucceſſe or fruit of converſion, by Dr. <hi>Preſton, Sibs, Criſpe,</hi> yet many before converted were confirmed and comforted by their words.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, the letter of Scripture, and the fleſh of Chriſt hath been highly ſet up by both the famous <hi>Goodwins,</hi> the one, Maſter <hi>John Goodwin</hi> like <hi>Apollos</hi> being migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Scriptures and ſtrength of reaſon; the other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:118421:17"/>in ſpirituall diſcourſes of Chriſts death, reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, aſcenſion, and interceſſion, yet much accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh; for he meddles not with the Myſtery of Chriſt in us, of his dying in us (as Mr. <hi>Dell</hi> in part diſcovers) but all of Chriſt without us, which though a truth, yet not the whole truth, nor that ſpirit and truth which Chriſt ſpake of;
<note place="margin">John 6.63. 2 Cor. 3.6.18.</note> for <hi>as the fleſh profiteth nothing, but the quickning ſpirit that dwelt therein;</hi> ſo the the Apoſtles had a <hi>miniſtery of the ſpirit</hi> to carry men through the fleſh of Chriſt into the Father, that eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Spirit dwelling in him and them, and ſo to draw them up into the ſame fellowſhip with himſelf.</p>
                  <p>Again this good man ſpeakes much of Chriſt in the fleſh, not as <hi>he is in the Father, and we in him, and be in us,</hi> which is the ſum of our ſpiritual knowledge, and all we ſhould know of Chriſt after his Aſcenſion, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.20.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, he brings us no further then to the <hi>vail of his fleſh,</hi> not <hi>through it into the holy of holieſt,</hi> into the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head it ſelf, that is, into the Father, for Chriſt was but our fore-runner, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 6.19, 20.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, though the vail of <hi>his fleſh</hi> be <hi>a new and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way into the holieſt,</hi> yet not that fleſh as <hi>living,</hi> but as dead and <hi>crucified, became the living way, Heb.</hi> 10.20. (as with God) I ſhall ſhew another time.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, that worthy man brings men to the <hi>way,</hi> but not to the <hi>Truth and Life:</hi> Now Chriſt was all, Firſt, the <hi>way, for no man cometh to the Father, but by me,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 14.6.</note> now 'tis a vain thing to keep men ſtill in the way, to ſtand ſtill in the way, and not to goe on by Chriſt into the Father, <hi>into the holieſt,</hi> and thus was Chriſt <hi>the Truth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 14.3.</note> alſo <hi>taking us into the Father with himſelf,</hi> for as this was <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life to know the Father to be the onely true God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh. 17.3.</note> 
                     <hi>and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt whom he hath ſent:</hi> ſo Chriſt was ſent, or God even the Father was manifeſt in his fleſh, that <hi>we might ſee God in us, as he was in him,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iohn 17.21, 23, 24.</note> 
                     <hi>and our life with him in God:</hi> Laſtly, thus <hi>Chriſt is the life,</hi> and thus he that
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:118421:18"/>hath the Son hath life, that is, the Son being once re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in us, reveals the Father in us alſo, God in our fleſh as in his, and we living with him in God alone, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.19, 20. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 5.11, 12.</p>
                  <p>This is the knowledge of Chriſt in the Spirit, and this is the fourth ſtep which ſome have attained to, holding forth Chriſt in the Spirit, as Mr. <hi>Sedgwick,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sterrie,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sprig</hi> and others, theſe with their fellows are nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Zion, yet are they not come into it; for as every Prophet ſhall one day <hi>be aſhamed of his viſion;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 13.4.</note> yea, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie it ſelf ſhall fail: So it is manifeſt theſe men are of a <hi>dark and deeper ſpeech then can be eaſily underſtood,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 33.19.</note> therefore it is not Zion, when there ſhall be ſuch a glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious appearance of God in men, that all ſhall ſee and hear him in them, and as they <hi>ſhall ſee eye to eye, when the Lord ſhall bring again</hi> Zion,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 52.8.</note> (or bring forth himſelf cleerly in us, who are now in captivity, or he rather captive in our fleſh) ſo men ſhall hear God himſelf in us, for ſo it is in the Hebrew, <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.23. not <hi>we have heard that God is with you,</hi> but (we will go with you for) <hi>we have heard God with you, and in you.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Then man ſhall be nothing, and God ſhall be all in all, yet man ſhall be all in God, and nothing but God ſhall appear in man. This glorious appearance of the great God in man, the <hi>three Shepherds,</hi> the Paſtors and Teachers doe <hi>indeed abhor,</hi> they <hi>hate his appearance,</hi> (as I ſaid) and he <hi>abhors</hi> all their performances.</p>
                  <p>But who are theſe three Shepherds? the Paſtors of Churches: What their cutting off is my former Letter ſhewed, to ſuffer the curſe of God, and contempt of men: How God cuts them off? It is by unchurching them, and by confounding or dividing them, the Lord doth firſt unchurch them, burns up the Church with fire, <hi>Zachariah</hi> 11.1. there he calls <hi>Lebanon to open the doors,</hi> that the <hi>fire may come in to burn up the talleſt Cedars.</hi> Whats Lebanon but the Temple, for it was built with that: Who are the Cedars? but the talleſt
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:118421:18"/>Members, the <hi>principall of the flock:</hi> What is the <hi>fire?</hi> but the Spirit of the Lord: as the Lord God calls upon <hi>Lebanon,</hi> ſo he commands that the <hi>Church doors</hi> may be open <hi>for the fire to enter,</hi> and the ſpirit to burn up all their chiefeſt members and Miniſters, for ſo it is <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>The mighty men, or the gallants are ſpoiled,</hi> yea, there is a <hi>howling of the ſhepherds for their glory is ſpoiled,</hi> v. 3. Their Church-fellowſhip and forms is that they glory in; God ſpoils them, <hi>and ſtains the pride of all their glory,</hi> yea, he burns it up; How? By fire; <hi>The baptiſme of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit and of fire</hi> was the firſt Goſpel-Ordinance,
<note place="margin">Acts 1.4, 5.</note> or that which firſt ſet up the <hi>Church in a Goſpel-order.</hi> Fire will be the laſt that ſhall burn up the Churches, who becauſe they would not, as the Primitive Saints did, wait for the Spirit to build them, the Spirit ſhall come to burn and conſume them at laſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, God cuts them off, confounds and divides them, he cuts them into three parts as we ſhall ſee by and by.</p>
                  <p>Thus then the <hi>three ſhepherds</hi> are the Paſtors of all the Churches or whole Miniſtery of the Church;
<note place="margin">Ezek. 16.30. Rev. 17.2.</note> for as the Apoſtate Jewiſh Church was a Type of the Chriſtian Church now under the Apoſtacie (the <hi>whoredomes of Iſrael,</hi> typifying the <hi>great whore,</hi> whoſe fornications and the wine thereof in their forms of doctrine and falſe worſhips) as we ſhall ſhew another time; ſo <hi>Junius</hi> well notes the three Shepherds to ſignifie the whole teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſtery of the Jewiſh Church,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid. Junium</hi> in Zach. 11.</note> for the Phariſees Sadduces, and Eſſenes (ſaith he) were the onely, Paſtors or Teachers, who did inſtruct the people in the Word of God, as Prelates, Presbyters, and Independents are the whole Miniſtery of the Church of <hi>England</hi> this day.</p>
                  <p>Theſe are divided not onely in Worſhip, and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, but in doctrine alſo, eſpecially in three things 1. In the free grace of God, which ſome call Antinomianiſm. 2. In the free-will of man, which otherscall Pelagianiſm. 3. In the death of Chriſt, or univerſal Redemption
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:118421:19"/>of mankind thereby, which both Presbyters and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendants abhorre as Paganiſme, though neareſt the <hi>Goſpel indeed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall not now ſhew the cauſe of all thoſe diviſions in Doctrine, being engaged onely at preſent to prove their defilements in the worſhip of God, and in their walking with men.</p>
                  <p>Yet this is one cauſe of their former difference and diviſions in Doctrine,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.42.</note> becauſe <hi>the Apoſtles Doctrine,</hi> being before all Goſpel-Ordinances, is out of order in the Churches,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.3. 2. Tim. 1.13.</note> who not content with that <hi>forme of ſound words,</hi> and <hi>wholſome Doctrine delivered</hi> by them, doe follow the childiſh Dictates of Fathers, the Decrees of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels, being a company of Biſhops, with ſuch Creeds, Confeſſions, and Catechiſmes, formed by them (and reformed Churches) whoſe conformities and fooleries in formes of worſhip, though our Churches cannot chuſe but ſee, yet with a blind devotion they follow all their formes of doctrine, not ſuffering a doubt or the leaſt debate to paſſe upon their reaſon and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment therein.</p>
                  <p>How injudicious this is with ingenuous men let all men judge,
<note place="margin">Iohn 3.12.</note> for if I <hi>tell you of earthly things,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>and yee beleeve not, how will yee beleeve if I tell you of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly?</hi> all outward worſhip is but an <hi>earthly thing:</hi> Now if all Fathers and former Churches have erred in worſhip, why not, I pray you, may they not erre in Doctrine, in heavenly and hidden things in the high Myſtery of God and of Chriſt? eſpecially ſeeing the Apoſtles did propheſie of <hi>ſuch deceit to come in this, by vain</hi> Philoſophy,
<note place="margin">Col. 2.8.</note> and metaphyſicall ſpeculations of the Deity, <hi>by the traditions and inventions of men, the rudiments of the world,</hi> the rudiments, that is, the A. B. C. or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Catechiſmes, which is the Religion of the world, and of little Children.</p>
                  <p>Another cauſe of diviſions in Doctrine is this, the confidence of men and Miniſters, who conceive, that
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:118421:19"/>Chriſtians know God and Chriſt already, whereas themſelves are ignorant of both,
<note place="margin">Rev. 1.7. 03 Rev. 5.2.</note> not minding that <hi>God is a Myſtery,</hi> and that the Myſtery of <hi>Chriſt hath been a ſealed Book</hi> ever ſince the Apoſtaſie, as I have ſhewn, in a book of <hi>neither Truth nor Error,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Nor Truth, nor Error, &amp;c. page 6.</note> 
                     <hi>nor Light nor Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, but in the evening there ſhall be Light.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Their darkneſſe and diviſions hath been cauſed by not <hi>knowing Chriſt in the Spirit, nor underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Myſtery of Chriſt,</hi> for all Chriſtian Religions have been doting onely on the fleſh of Chriſt: See the Papiſts how they look upon Chriſt in a Picture; ſo Proteſtants have their <hi>pleaſant Pictures alſo,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 2.16, Ezek 16.17.</note> 
                     <hi>the Image of a Male,</hi> as the Prophets phraſe it, that is, fleſhly <hi>ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of Chriſt,</hi> which they adore and deifie: thus the <hi>Arminians</hi> and <hi>Socinians</hi> goe no farther than Chriſt after the fleſh, and the laſt eſpecially, though religious and moſt learned men, yet look no higher than fleſh; yea, the eternall Spirit and infinite God they confine to a place in Heaven, where, ſay they, his eſſentiall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence is, though his power be every where, a very carnall conceit of God and of Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But what myſtery can the <hi>Socinian</hi> ſee in the Man Chriſt, if the Man be not God, or <hi>God manifeſt in fleſh?</hi> is not the Man Chriſt <hi>the Myſtery of God? Rev.</hi> 10.7.
<note place="margin">Col. 2.2. Eph. 3.5.</note> And how can <hi>the Myſtery of God and of Chriſt be mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt but by the Spirit?</hi> 'tis neither ſtrength of reaſon, nor reading of Scripture, but the Spirit onely, even the <hi>Spirit of Revelation,</hi> that can prove the Godhead of Chriſt, therefore the Apoſtle himſelf had it, <hi>not as he received it of man, nor as he was taught it, but by the Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when it pleaſed God to reveal his Son in him, &amp;c. <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.12, 15.</p>
                  <p>For how could the Apoſtle, preaching to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, prove the Godhead of Chriſt by Scripture to them, who owned neither Chriſt nor Scriptures? But <hi>Chriſt ſpeaking in him,</hi> that is, Chriſt in the Spirit,
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 13.3.</note> God powerfully acting and appearing in <hi>Pauls</hi> fleſh, did ſo
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:118421:20"/>manifeſt the Myſtery to them, that by <hi>the power of God working in him mightily,</hi> he was able to preſent every man in Chriſt, that is, <hi>in God,</hi> and God in them, and <hi>they his Off-ſpring,</hi> and thus did he prove the Godhead of Chriſt,
<note place="margin">Col. 1.28, 29.</note> and that God would judge <hi>the world by the man Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> even by the manifeſtation of God in <hi>the Saints,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 17.28, 29, 32.</note> 
                     <hi>who ſhould judge the world with them</hi> and in him, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.2.</p>
                  <p>Indeed to the Jewes, who acknowledged the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, by Scriptures he proved that Chriſt was God, yet not the Godhead of Chriſt by that, for as Chriſt never ſaid that he was God (but <hi>ſent by God</hi>) ſo he ſhewed his Godhead to <hi>be the Father dwelling in him, and doing all his works,</hi> which though neither the Jewes nor Diſciples clearly ſaw in the dayes of his fleſh; yet when he ſhould <hi>depart to the Father,</hi> and the Spirit or <hi>Promiſe of the Father</hi> ſhould be ſent, then the power of God appearing in their fleſh as in his, he <hi>ſhewes them the Father plainly,</hi> for as <hi>no man knowes the Father but the Sonne, and he to whom the Sonne reveales him;</hi> ſo I ſaid before, that God, even the Father, muſt reveal the Sonne in us, by the Spirit of Revelation to us, elſe there is no knowing the Godhead of Chriſt at all, <hi>John</hi> 14.10. <hi>John</hi> 16.25, 27, 28.</p>
                  <p>For <hi>no man can ſay that Jeſus is the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12.3.</note> 
                     <hi>but by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;</hi> alas man, what myſtery is it that Chriſt is God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God made the Man ſo? becauſe God gave him that name? gave him that power and glory as God? 'tis true, that Chriſt, even the Sonne of God, had all by gift of the Father,
<note place="margin">Iohn 5.19, 22, 26. verſes.</note> 
                     <hi>The Sonne could doe nothing of himſelf, God gave him even the Spirit, gave him authority to judge, gave him to have life in himſelf</hi> (whereas we have all of him,
<note place="margin">Math. 28.18. Iohn 17.2. Phil. 2.6, 9. Heb. 1.8, 9.</note> and by him) <hi>God gave him glory, all power in heaven and earth; God gave him a name above every name,</hi> yea, <hi>gave him to be called God, for God, his God, annointed him to it</hi> above his fellowes; all this proves not the Godhead
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:118421:20"/>of Chriſt, but that he was the <hi>Man Gods fellow, that is, equall with God, in the form if God,</hi> as 'tis parallell'd by the Apoſtle and Prophet, <hi>Zach.</hi> 13.7. <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.6, 9.</p>
                  <p>Therefore what <hi>Socinus</hi> ſaith, that Chriſt is God, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God gave him that name, that power, that glory, and honour, is no myſtery, for God can give <hi>to a Worme, to threſh the mountaines, to throw down the earth, to deſtroy and judge the world,</hi> Iſai 41.14, 15. Jer. 51.20.</p>
                  <p>But what's the Myſtery of Chriſt? <hi>wait for the Spirit to manifeſt it</hi> to thee and me: <hi>Till the ſeventh Angell ſound,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 10.7.</note> 
                     <hi>the Myſtery of God ſhall not be finiſhed nor fully known.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What a madneſſe is it then, for men to warr and wrangle about that they know not? Is it not better for us, to wait in peace and patience, forbearing one another, and embracing one another in love, till the Lord God appear in all?</p>
                  <p>I ſhall therefore crave pardon of all men, becauſe I cannot chuſe but ſay, that <hi>no man yet knowes God, nor Chriſt, nor himſelf;</hi> this makes the difference and divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion (as I ſaid before) becauſe men are ſo confident, and therefore contend of the free Grace of God, the free Will of Man, and the Death of Chriſt, yet they know not <hi>God as he is,</hi> nor what <hi>Man is in God,</hi> nor what <hi>the Man-God Chriſt is,</hi> in the Myſtery, how in God, and how he is in man: Oh yee <hi>Proteſtants, Papiſts, Arminians,</hi> and <hi>Socinians,</hi> anſwer me this one queſtion; Why did the higheſt Apoſtle beg the prayers of all the Churches, that he might know the <hi>Myſtery of Chriſt,</hi> that he might manifeſt it, and that he might <hi>ſpeak as he ought to ſpeak?</hi> Eph. 6.19, 20. Col. 4.3, 4.</p>
                  <p>You think you know Chriſt, and can preach him well enough, we ſhall be all ſilent, and God himſelf ſhall ſpeak at laſt, and ſpeak himſelf, and manifeſt himſelf unto men: Oh that men could watch and wait in love together to that day!</p>
                  <p>This is the laſt thing I had to obſerve, that all the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:118421:21"/>
                     <hi>ſpeaking and preachings of men will be ſilenced by God</hi> when the Lord appeares: Pray but obſerve in thoſe four ſteps before mentioned, of Gods appearance in men, how the power, efficacie, and fruit of Converſion hath decreaſed: The Doctrine of Free-grace converted fewer than that legall teaching before; the preaching of Chriſt after the fleſh by the pureſt Churches hath had leſſe converts yet; yea, thoſe who preach Chriſt in the Spirit, the moſt ſeraphick Sermons, call in but few Sinners, though ſome Saints may be raiſed, others proud fleſh rankle thereby; but as for the Spirit of Jeſus, where does it appear in mens preaching or pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, or the power of godlineſſe?</p>
                  <p>That which I conclude from this is, that <hi>God is going out, and departing from all the preachings of men,</hi> that men may give themſelves wholly to publick acts of love one to another, and to all mankind; therefore all <hi>religious formes</hi> ſhall fall, that the <hi>power of righteouſneſſe</hi> may riſe and appear in all:
<note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13. Rev. 21.22.</note> 
                     <hi>The new Heaven and new Earth, where dwelleth Righteouſneſſe, hath no form</hi> of Religion there.</p>
                  <p>I ſee 'tis haſtening by many things, and this to me is the leaſt prophetick providence and experience in the preſent powers of the Nation: when the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> firſt began, oh what ſpeakings were there? what Speeches of ſeverall Members of the houſe of Commons were printed every week? but now the Common-wealth comes on, there is more of Action done every day, and though the Parliament many times ſay more than they doe, yet they doe more than they ſay, which is beſt of all.</p>
                  <p>Again, I cannot but obſerve, that as <hi>the falling of a Sparrow,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Math. 10.30.</note> 
                     <hi>or the ſmalleſt hair of our heads, is ſubject to the ſpeciall</hi> providence of God; ſo 'tis remarkable, that all the Parliaments Ordinances are now turned into Acts, for Acts indeed are better than Ordinances, theſe are of form, thoſe of power; the Army was beſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed when they were about their Ordinances, their
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:118421:21"/>Guns, going forth for common freedome, thoſe were their Acts, and God did bleſſe them therein in all their publick actings, and in their publick Spirits, but as for their publick ſpeakings, their Declarations, Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Remonſtrances, 'tis not worth a ruſh: So are their Councels of War, when judging the Conſciences of men in the Myſtery of Chriſt (a moſt high preſumption:) yea, all their faſting and prayer before God is not worth a pins head, till they repent and return to their firſt principles, to the power of Righteouſneſſe, to Juſtice, and Mercy to the Nation, without all ſelf-ſeeking, ſtriving for the univerſall good of mankind, even for Papiſts and for Jewes themſelves, to live with freedome and comfort among us, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.9, 10, 11. compared with <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.4, 5.</p>
                  <p>This is the <hi>glorious appearance of the great God,</hi> not to talke and prate of things, but to be working and acting, to be ever doing good, as <hi>Chriſt did alwayes to all,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 10.38.</note> and though there was a Miniſtery of men once to ſpeak alſo glad tydings and good things to men, yet ſince the Apoſtacy, that <hi>Apoſtolick Miniſtery being ſilenced,</hi> and the <hi>manifold gifts of the Spirit</hi> ceaſed, and no man ſent of God to <hi>preach the Goſpel which the holy Spirit ſent down from Heaven,</hi> all is but earth and man that is ſaid,
<note place="margin">1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.12.</note> the number of the <hi>beaſt being the number of a man,</hi> Rev. 13.16.</p>
                  <p>And though God hath hitherto <hi>fed and led the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the wilderneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 12.6.</note> 
                     <hi>and cauſed men to miniſter ſome truth and peace to his</hi> people under the Apoſtacy, yet this was but <hi>his Free-grace,</hi> and high <hi>Prerogative of love,</hi> who as not tyed to meanes, ſo by a falſe Miniſtery could convey light and comfort to his own; but now God is pouring vials of wrath on that which was once lovely, upon the Sun and air, upon the light of man, upon the meanes, and thoſe mediums that receive it, Rev. 16.8.17.</p>
                  <p>Again, ſeeing the man of ſinne, the myſtery of ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:118421:22"/>is now more revealed in the Temple of God than ever, and the miniſtery of men is diſcovered every day not to be of Gods appointment, as Prelates, and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, and pureſt Independent Paſtors, cut off by the Lord himſelf: it is therefore judged, that not onely the whole Miniſtry, but all the preachings of men, will ſhortly be ſilenced by the glorious appearance of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Be ſilent O all fleſh, for the Lord is raiſed out of his holy habitation, Zach.</hi> 2.13. Why if man be ſilent, what will God doe among men? <hi>A Father of the fatherleſſe, and a Judge of the widow, is God in his holy habitation, Pſal.</hi> 68.5. that is, God will ſo appear in men, that inſtead of ſpeakings, they ſhall goe forth in actings of love to mankind, and to the miſerable part thereof, to the <hi>poor, to the oppreſſed, to the fatherleſſe, and the widow,</hi> and to all that want that which we abound in.</p>
                  <p>As this was once <hi>pure Religion, and undefiled before God even the Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iam. 1.27.</note> 
                     <hi>to viſit the Fatherleſſe and widow in their afflictions, and to keep our ſelves unſpotted of the world;</hi> ſo the neglect of this is charged on the Apoſtate Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1, 23. <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.28.</p>
                  <p>Alas, what is it to ſend Preachers abroad before the burthens and oppreſſions of the people be eaſed? <hi>Iſrael it ſelf could not hear,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Exod. 6.9.</note> 
                     <hi>becauſe of the ſore bondage in Aegypt;</hi> I ſay, not all burthens taken off, becauſe the charge of the Common wealth encreaſeth, but why may not rich Citizens, racking Landlords in the Country, and mighty moneyed men, be made immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately to rife in their payments, that poor Farmers, La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourers, and honeſt Tradeſmen may be ſpared? Why not oppreſſion be preſently eaſed, at leaſt of Lawyers and Tithes? Why not a Treaſury for the poor, when ſo many thouſands a year can be found out to give to the rich? would that hinder the publick more than this? It is the goodneſſe of the State indeed, to honour and conferre gifts on high deſerving men, but it is diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:118421:22"/>and baſe for ſuch to receive it, who neglecting the publick good, ſeek their private gain, who would ſeem to be Saints and ſelf-denying men, yet forgetting their vowes to God and men, care not though the poor and the oppreſſed ſink, ſtarve, and dye, ſo they may live fat, and full, and free from thoſe evils.</p>
                  <p>Gifts are as bad as bribes, when Juſtice and great things are to be done in a Nation, for as a bribe blindes the eyes, and they <hi>ſhall never ſee the King in his beauty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſay. 32.15. Eccl. 7.7.</note> 
                     <hi>who ſhake not their hands from holding of bribes, and deſpiſe not the gain of Oppreſſion;</hi> ſo <hi>a gift deſtroyes the heart,</hi> that the moſt publick ſpiritted man dares not think a good thought, much leſſe to ſpeak or act for common free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and the good of mankind, while money ſtops the mouth, choakes and <hi>deſtroyes the heart.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>They ſay indeed the time is not yet come, but <hi>is it a time to receive monie?</hi> ſaid <hi>Eliſha:</hi> Oh ſay others,
<note place="margin">2 King. 5.26. Iſai. 51.14.</note> you are to haſty, &amp;c. but the <hi>captive exile haſtened that he might be lcoſed, and that he ſhould not dye in the pit, nor that his bread ſhould fail:</hi> If theſe men were bamſhed but for a year, or their Babes without bread for a day, they would not delay juſtice and mercy to men, ſeeing the Lord <hi>comes riding on a ſwift cloud,</hi> to judge and raign, and to <hi>haſten Righteouſneſs,</hi> Iſai. 16.5.</p>
                  <p>Let <hi>Mercarius Politicus</hi> tell you the reaſon of State, and ſhew you <hi>if men were religious ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d, that is, righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, juſt, honeſt, plain, ſimple hearted people, they might quickly doe</hi> what they ſay: what's that? <hi>Take away the iniquity of the Land in one day;</hi> the iniquity, that is,
<note place="margin">Zach 3 9.</note> the oppreſſion, &amp;c. <hi>I will take it away in one day;</hi> how ſo ſpray?</p>
                  <p>When God ſhall appear in men,
<note place="margin">See the Lord of hoſts, or Armies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, pag. 23.</note> 
                     <hi>and men act in the immediate power of God,</hi> when the power that God and man hath put into their hands is improved to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, <hi>without fear of man,</hi> and with full <hi>confidence in God,</hi> oh what a <hi>world of good might be done in one day?</hi> all the proud enemies, oppreſſors, the unrighteous riches, the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:118421:23"/>unjuſt gaines, the great reveneues ſuddenly got, yea all the <hi>iniquity of the Land would be taken away in one day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This would be <hi>Goſpel indeed, and glad tydings to the poor,</hi> and make all the oppreſſed in the Land to ſing, for this is <hi>the everlaſting Goſpel</hi> which ſhall be preached, <hi>not in wordbut in power,</hi> not as the Goſpel at firſt, in ſpeaking, or <hi>preachings, but in publick actings, the everlaſting Goſpel</hi> ſhall goe forth in the laſt times, as I ſhall hint anon, and another time (with God) more fully prove, that the <hi>preaching of the everlaſting Goſpel</hi> is not the miniſtery of man, nor is that <hi>Angel</hi> a man or Miniſter; but the <hi>Angel of the Covenant, Chriſt in us,</hi> God in our fleſh, that is, God fully manifeſt in us ſhall miniſter himſelf to us, God ſhall miniſter himſelf to men, a pure Miniſtery of the Spirit ſhall be, the Spirit ſhall onely miniſter both light and love among men, ſalvation, and ſtrength, ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency, and fulneſſe of all good things to the whole Creation at laſt.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>glorious appearance of the great God and Saviour in men,</hi> is that which is moſt <hi>abhorred by Miniſters and Paſtors, three Shepheards,</hi> whom the Lord <hi>loaths and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides</hi> becauſe they will not be drawn up to union, and love to mankind, to whom they are rather cruell, <hi>their throat an open Sepulchre,</hi> and their feet <hi>ſwift to ſhed bloud;</hi> that is, they will ſpeak no <hi>good will to man,</hi> but ſwallow down the moſt and deſtroy them, not owning <hi>all men as their own fleſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 58.7.</note> and God the eternall Spirit dwelling in them, therefore God divides the Shepheards with their flockes, daſhing one againſt another, cauſing <hi>every man of them to eat the fleſh of his brother,</hi> Zach. 11.9.</p>
                  <p>True, it is but <hi>fleſh and fleſhly formes</hi> the Churches fight and contend for, the cauſe of all the contention is in the Shepheards or the Miniſters, the Church-members, poor ſoules would be quiet, and come up again to walk in the Spirit; but becauſe the Members will follow, not the Head, but their fellowes, Members and Miniſters,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:118421:23"/>God <hi>gives them up to their King,</hi> v. 6. Who is that? Sure ſome chief Paſtor who commands in Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth: Well, for this, God takes no more care of the Church, but divides them alſo; <hi>He breaks the Covenant which he made with all the people,</hi> v. 10.</p>
                  <p>The Independent Church was built once on a <hi>Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> now being aſhamed of that, they call it a <hi>confeſſion,</hi> others an <hi>ragreement,</hi> God breaks all in pieces even the Covenant. Firſt his <hi>ſtaffe,</hi> Beautie, that is, the <hi>unitie of the Spirit,</hi> v. 10. then his <hi>ſtaffe bonds,</hi> the bond of Peace, for the <hi>brotherhood between Judah and Iſrael is broken, verſe</hi> 14.</p>
                  <p>How cleer doth this appear in the preſent Churches, who by a Law call none brothers but ſuch of their own ſocieties, no Saint whatſoever, nor yet Chriſt were he among them would they call brother, unleſſe he were of a Church way, and of theirs alſo, therefore the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhoood between <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (the Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and baptized Churches) is broken.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Great and marvellous are thy works Lord God almighty,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 15.3.</note> 
                     <hi>juſt and true are thy wayes thou King of Saints?</hi> How juſt is it for God to divide thoſe Churches that divide them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from Saints? How true is their diviſion, when the very <hi>Brotherhood</hi> is broken?</p>
                  <p>Oh <hi>love the brotherhood,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.17.</note> that cannot be ſaith the Prophet, for there is nothing but wrath and wars to be among them, they muſt be divided and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided alſo: <hi>I will deliver the men every one into the hand of his neighbour, or fellow member, and into the hand of his King or Paſtor,</hi> for ſuch are called Kings in Scripture,
<note place="margin">Zach. 11.6.</note> Princes of the Sanctuary. Again, ſaith God, <hi>I will not feed you, that that dyeth let it die, and that that is to be cut off, let it be cut off, and let the reſt eat every one the fleſh of another,</hi> v. 9. that is, thoſe fellow-Members who were more moderate and peaceable minded men, not given to common diviſion, are yet deſtroyed and die in their ſpirits, by being in Church-fellowſhip, for God
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:118421:24"/>breaks the <hi>Covenant that he made with all the people,</hi> v. 19.</p>
                  <p>This is that I ſhewed in the mountaines from <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiel</hi> 37.3. That, <hi>All the people of God this day are a dead divided people,</hi> not onely gathered Churches, but ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Saints, theſe in their fleſh, thoſe in their forms and fellowſhips.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, they are as dry <hi>bones of the valley,</hi> yea, bones ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>dry</hi> lying in the <hi>open valley,</hi> the loweſt part of the earth, and it is the <hi>open valley,</hi> every one above them who are on the hills may behold and ſee how <hi>dead</hi> and <hi>dry</hi> they are; very dry ſaith he, having neither skin, nor ſinew, nor ſtrength, nor ſpirit, nor yet fleſh indeed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, not the letter of Scripture for any of their publique Worſhips, common Prayers, &amp;c. nor yet in their walkings doth the fleſh Chriſt appear upon them in meekneſs and lowlineſs of heart, yea they are not ſo lowly and loving, as once they were, ſo humble and ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly minded, ſo ſelf denying and dying to the world. And as they are dead ſo divided into two ſticks, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 37.16.
<note place="margin">See Zeph. 39. a pure lip and perfect love or union will not be on earth, till the earth or Church, in her diviſions and defile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments be burnt up with fire, which is <hi>Babylons</hi> laſt plague, Rev. 18 8. then men will ſerve or worſhip God in Spirit, and with one con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent or ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</note> they are not now called <hi>branches, but ſticks</hi> dry, ſapleſs things without any ſhew of ſpiritual life, yea with out hope to riſe here on earth, as themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, <hi>v.</hi> 11.</p>
                  <p>But I have better hopes of you beloved, then your ſelves have: All the Churches indeed ſhall fall but the Saints therein ſhall riſe, <hi>Oh my people</hi> ſaith God, <hi>I will open your graves, and cauſe you to come forth out of your graves,</hi> v. 12.</p>
                  <p>But there the people of God yet are, and this the Lord would haue them know this day, although they will not that they are all in <hi>Babylon, dead dry bon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>divided ſticks:</hi> Dead in <hi>their formes,</hi> divided in <hi>their fellowſhips,</hi> and defiled in both, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.9. But <hi>Babylon</hi> is yet di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into <hi>three parts,</hi> for ſince the Apoſtacie the Churches have been ſtill divided <hi>into three parts,</hi> as the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latine</hi> Churches of old, and the <hi>Affrican</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:118421:24"/>Church that made the third, there was the <hi>Eaſtern, We<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern,</hi> and <hi>Southern</hi> Churches: So in the <hi>North</hi> at the firſt Reformation, the <hi>Calviniſt, Lutheran,</hi> and <hi>Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi> Thus it is in <hi>England,</hi> the <hi>Prelatick, Presbiterian,</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> Churches are <hi>Babylon</hi> divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into three parts.</p>
                  <p>The Apoſtolike Churches or Churches of Chriſt were but <hi>one bodie,</hi> had but <hi>one Baptiſm,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eph. 4.4.</note> as there was but <hi>one Spirit</hi> leading all the Saints in one Church way, one <hi>way of worſhip,</hi> one <hi>Church government</hi> was among all the Saints, though there were differences between bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and brother, yea, between one Apoſtle and another, yet never was there a diviſion <hi>between Church and Church</hi> as in <hi>Babylon</hi> this day, for the Spirit being then but one, kept the body in one Baptiſm. But now the Churches are become <hi>three bodies,</hi> and theſe have <hi>three Baptiſms;</hi> Presbyterians <hi>baptiſe the whole Nation;</hi> Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents the <hi>children of beleevers onely;</hi> the baptized Churches <hi>beleevers themſelves:</hi> Here is <hi>Babylon</hi> in three parts: Again the baptized Churches are ſubdivided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to three parts, one Church is for <hi>free will,</hi> a ſecond for <hi>univerſal Redemption,</hi> a third count themſelves more Orthodox in Doctrine, as the Church of <hi>England:</hi> Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe three baptized Churches dare communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate one with another, Oh <hi>Babylon! Babylon</hi> is fallen is fallen, for <hi>Babylons</hi> fall is by diviſion and confuſion;
<note place="margin">Iſai. 10.26, 27 Iudg. 7.25. Ioel 3.12.</note> the Prophet calls it, <hi>The ſlaughter of Midian,</hi> for the <hi>Midianites</hi> were deſtroyed by their mutual diviſion. This another Prophet calls the <hi>valley of Jehoſhaphat,</hi> for as the ſcattered <hi>bones lay in the valley,</hi> Ezek. 37.1. So the valley of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> hath ſome reference to the dry bones, and the divided ſticks in <hi>Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whats the valley of <hi>Jehoſaphat?</hi> 'Tis the divided ſtate of men oppoſing the appearance of God in his people. See 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.23. there is <hi>Moah, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>Mount Seir,</hi> all three of kin to the true Church of God, which thoſe three came againſt, as the preſent
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:118421:25"/>Churches pretend to the Primitive Church of Chriſt, which yet they oppoſe in the Spirit.</p>
                  <p>Well, let us look into the <hi>valley of Jehoſaphat,</hi> thither <hi>cauſe thy mighty ones to come down O Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Joel</hi> 3.11. Oh how many mighty ones, and high ſpirited men are come down <hi>to the valley of Jehoſaphat, into divided Churches, Moah, Ammon,</hi> and <hi>mount Seir:</hi> Firſt, two are againſt one, then one againſt another, for <hi>Moah,</hi> and <hi>Ammon,</hi> ſtood up againſt <hi>mount Seir utterly to ſlay and deſtroy, and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of mount Seir, each man helped to deſtroy one another,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.23.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was with the <hi>Prelatick, Presbyterian,</hi> and <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent</hi> Churches, theſe two laſt <hi>ſtood up, utterly to ſlay and deſtroy</hi> the firſt both Root and Branch, and now they <hi>help to deſtroy one another,</hi> as Independent and bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized Churches both againſt Presbytery, and now <hi>theſe two againſt each other:</hi> Yea, the baptized Churches them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves are divided into three parts, are now in deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction by <hi>their own diviſions:</hi> Sure it is by the <hi>annointing</hi> all this is done, the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the Lord in their fleſh, which would unite doth now divide them, becauſe they will not hear <hi>what the Spirit ſaith to the Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore it is ſaid before 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.22. <hi>The Lord ſet ambuſhments againſt the children of</hi> Moab, Ammon, <hi>and mount Seir,</hi> &amp;c. an ambuſhment in <hi>ſecret and ſudden aſſault of an enemie</hi> unawares: Oh how <hi>ſecretly and ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly</hi> hath the Lord come upon the Churches in their <hi>march</hi> and <hi>Church-way?</hi> how hath he <hi>divided them one againſt another,</hi> before they were aware of it. This is the <hi>Lords work,</hi> and the <hi>wonder of men,</hi> that men who are all godly cannot joyn in <hi>one Church-way?</hi> why they will not, they ſhall not, they cannot, for God <hi>divides them in Jacob, and ſcatters them in Iſrael.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As this is <hi>Babylons</hi> judgement to fall by diviſion, ſo it is the judgement of God on the Churches, for in the <hi>valley of Jehoſhaphat he ſits to judge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:118421:25"/>
                  <p>That which I have heard to be Mr. <hi>Brightmans</hi> opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Mr. <hi>Sterries</hi> ſince, was given into my Spirit long ago, that as the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia,</hi> ſignifie the <hi>State of the Apoſtolike Churches</hi> inclining to an <hi>apoſtaſie:</hi> So <hi>Laodicea</hi> the <hi>laſt tipifies the latter Churches</hi> this day, who indeed ſhall be the <hi>laſt in the world,</hi> and the fall of all ſhall be firſt in <hi>England,</hi> for as Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> holds <hi>Laodicea</hi> to be the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſo the Churches here are <hi>Laodicea</hi> indeed, lukewarm, without heat, or the Baptiſm of fire at all, the Lord condemnes the other Churches in ſome things, yet in ſomething he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends them, but the Church of <hi>Laodicea</hi> he commends not at all, but condemns altogether, becauſe ſhe was <hi>well, and wanting nothing,</hi> no Church-order, no Ordinance is wanting to them.</p>
                  <p>Whats <hi>Laodicea</hi> in Greek,
<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but the <hi>judgement of the people,</hi> the people of God are judged indeed in the <hi>val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley of Jehoſaphat</hi> this day, by their mutuall diviſions to their utter deſtruction.</p>
                  <p>Therefore thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Three ſhepherds I cut off in one moneth.</hi> What's this <hi>moneth?</hi> Sure it is a Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. In general it is very ſhortly, as <hi>Junius</hi> before, for the Lord will now doe a <hi>ſhort work on the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 9.28. Iſai. 19.1.</note> he comes riding on a <hi>ſwift cloud</hi> to judge; yea, the Lord <hi>is a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs toe, and a ſwift witneſſe</hi> againſt the Churches,
<note place="margin">Mal. 3.5.</note> he comes <hi>quickly,</hi> and he will make <hi>but ſhort work with them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will not ſpeak of the Popiſh Church which conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſo many hundreds of yeers, look but into our own land in theſe laſt dayes, wherein the myſterie of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath been moſt manifeſt, not onely by the Spirit, but by ſenſible experience, and the event of things in a very little time.
<note place="margin">The King could give them no more time. The Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment gave them juſt ſo much.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Prelacie upheld by <hi>Kingly Power</hi> continued about ſeventy years, inſlaving the people of God, like <hi>Iſraels captivitie of old in Babylon.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Presbyterie reigned but three <hi>years and a half</hi> (the time of the <hi>Beaſt</hi>) by <hi>Parliamentarie Authoritie,</hi> for no
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:118421:26"/>longer according to Ordinance their time was to laſt.
<note place="margin">The Armie cannot give ſo much time as that, for <hi>time ſhall be no more</hi> Rev. 10.6. nor yet <hi>times, nor half a time,</hi> for thats the 42. <hi>moneths,</hi> the <hi>Dragons</hi> time. Revel. 13.5.42 <hi>moneths</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>three years</hi> and <hi>a half,</hi> that is <hi>time, times, and half a time, time</hi> is one year, <hi>times</hi> two-years, and <hi>half a year</hi> is the half time which ſhall be no more ſaith <hi>John,</hi> 'tis now but a moneth, nor forty two, nor time at all.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Independency is down in a <hi>moneth,</hi> thats a ſhorter time then the former, they are fallen before they riſe, the whole Armie cannot help them up again.</p>
                  <p>But what is this moneth? It is that of the <hi>wild Aſſe in the Wilderneſs,</hi> the Lord compares the Church to this, <hi>Jer,</hi> 2.24. <hi>A wild Aſſe uſed to the Wilderneſs, that ſnuffeth up the wind at her pleaſure, in her occaſion who can turn her away, all they that ſeek her will not weary themſelves, in her moneth they ſhall find her.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What is the <hi>moneth</hi> that we may find <hi>the Aſſe,</hi> for men weary themſelves in vain to ſeek her, ſhe is <hi>ſo wild,</hi> and in the <hi>wilderneſs</hi> alſo, where ſhe <hi>holds up her head,</hi> and <hi>ſnuffs the wind</hi> as ſhe goes, neither will <hi>ſhe be turned out of her way,</hi> yet in <hi>her moneth ſhe is found;</hi> Whats that! It is the <hi>moneth that ſhe is ready to bear or bring forth,</hi> when ſhe is full of pain and travell, when the <hi>wild Aſſe</hi> is in a <hi>ſuffering condition</hi> ſhe may be found.</p>
                  <p>Thus it was with the Churches; The Prelates thought themſelves Preachers of the Goſpel, how high did they hold their heads, <hi>and ſnuffe the wind as they went,</hi> but when their ſuffering time came, the <hi>ſpirits of Princes</hi> were cut off, the proudeſt Prelate dared not open his mouth for his eares, that ſhewed him an Aſſe, for if he had been as he ſaid a Preacher of the Goſpel, all the Parliaments of the world ſhould not have ſtopt his mouth, but they had no more to ſay when they came to ſuffer, then without ſeeking a man might find them to be no Miniſters of the Goſpel, <hi>for their moneth was</hi> come.</p>
                  <p>It was juſt ſo with the Presbyters, when in power with the Parliament, they alſo were as <hi>wild as the Aſſe</hi> in the <hi>Wilderneſs,</hi> as proud as the Prelates, and held up their heads as high, and opened their mouths (againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) as Miniſters of the Goſpel alſo, but when <hi>the moneth</hi> of their ſorrows and ſufferings come to an end, they
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:118421:26"/>will be dumb <hi>as the Aſſe,</hi> and as Biſhops were, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs God by a Miracle open their mouth, as <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe to ſpeak freely, the next countermand that comes from the Powers can ſilence them, or if they ſuffer the loſſe of Tithes, all their mouthes are ſtopt at once, for <hi>their moneth</hi> is come, they are cut off by God, and can preach no more.</p>
                  <p>Well, the Independent Paſtors and Teachers their moneth comes (and that in one day as <hi>Babylons</hi> plague did) I will not compare theſe wiſe men to the Aſſe in the Wilderneſs, yet truly they will not be turned from their way,
<note place="margin">Hoſ. 12.1.</note> but ſnuffe the wind as they goe (<hi>for it is wind that</hi> Ephraim <hi>feeds on</hi>) Oh, when will their moneth be? Whence can their ſufferings ariſe, ſeeing the whole State, and the higheſt Souldierie is for them? For all this they muſt ſuffer, all the world cannot ſave them, but what ſhall their ſufferings be? Surely <hi>not from man, nor by man, but by the Lord God they ſhall ſuffer,</hi> as it is cleer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly foretold, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 31.8, 9. <hi>The Aſſyrian is the laſt Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor,</hi> for <hi>Egypt</hi> was before. The Churches this day doe <hi>oppreſſe not onely men in their States, Mic.</hi> 2.2, 8, 9. but the <hi>ſpirits of men,</hi> verſ. 6. Yea, the <hi>Spirit of God</hi> alſo, verſ. 7.</p>
                  <p>The preſent Churches I look upon as the <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> the laſt oppreſſor that ſhall be in the Land, this is the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian that ſhall fall?</hi> How! not <hi>by man, and the ſword not of a mean man <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> devour him, Iſai.</hi> 31.8. How ſhall the Aſſyrians fall be then? Firſt, by fear. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, by fire. <hi>The ſinners of Zion are afraid already, and begin to fly to their ſtrong holds,</hi> and hope in an Armie or arm of fleſh, <hi>v.</hi> 8. What makes them <hi>fear and fly?</hi> Oh there is an <hi>Enſign ſet up in the Saints,</hi> v. 9. the glorious ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of God in the <hi>ſcattered Saints</hi> makes the <hi>ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered Churches</hi> quake and fear; but where is the <hi>fire?</hi> Why it is in Zion, <hi>and his furnace in Jeruſalem,</hi> v. 9. What is <hi>Zion but the Saints in whom God dwels,</hi> or in whom God diſcovers himſelf to be. Is he not in the Churches
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:118421:27"/>alſo? Yea, the Lord is there among them, the <hi>everlaſting burnings is in them,</hi> yea, they ſhall finde and feel ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that <hi>conſuming fire</hi> to break forth upon them, and to <hi>burn up all their fleſh and forms.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the judgement of God ſtill on the Churches, becauſe they would haſten to a Church-way, not waiting for the <hi>Baptiſm of the Spirit, and of fire</hi> to ſet them in a Goſpel-order, or to ſhew <hi>them a higher glory to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed in them;</hi> therefore a fire ſhall come forth of their own bowels to burn them, that is the fire of his jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie: Thus they are gone from one fire into another, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> tels them, <hi>They ſhall go out from one fire and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother fire ſhall devour them,</hi> Ezek. 15.7. they are gone out of the <hi>fire</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> the <hi>fire of his jealouſie</hi> ſhall conſume them, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.3. I ſpeak not now of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons but of that oppreſſive. principle and fleſhly power, thats the Aſſyrian in them, as I ſaid once, that of old the people of God <hi>were in Babylon,</hi> but now <hi>Babylon</hi> is <hi>in them,</hi> eſpecially in the Churches called the <hi>oppreſſor, the golden Citie,</hi> Iſai. 14.4.</p>
                  <p>But ſee how the fire is come in to the Churches as we ſaid before, there not onely the Cedars, the talleſt and higheſt members are burnt,
<note place="margin">Zach. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>v.</hi> 2. but all the mighty men (or gallants) are ſpoiled, even the Miniſters or Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, for the howling of the Shepherds is heard on high, <hi>v.</hi> 3. &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Pray obſerve in all the Proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> what plagues are foretold to fall upon the <hi>Paſtors and Shepherds of Iſrael;</hi> but eſpecially <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> Ch. 25.34, 35, 36. where there is a great <hi>howling of the Shepherds and principall of the flock, for the day of their diſperſion is come,</hi> or their diviſion as we ſaid before, <hi>Zach.</hi> 11.6, 9. Here they doe <hi>eat every one the fleſh of another,</hi> of his fellow or brother, as the Hebrew reads; thus the fellow-members fall out, and the <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood is broken</hi> between the Churches, <hi>v.</hi> 14. Why? becauſe their Shepherds are <hi>cut off</hi> in one <hi>moneth;</hi> whats that? we have ſaid already 'tis the <hi>day of their ſufferings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:118421:27"/>
                  <p>But there may be another ſenſe of this <hi>moneth,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that of the Prophet, <hi>Hoſea</hi> 5.6, 7. <hi>They ſhall gee with their flocks to ſeek the Lord, but they ſhall not find him, he hath withdrawn himſelf from them; they have dealt treacherouſly againſt the Lord, for they have begotten ſtrange children, now ſhall a moneth devour them with their portions;</hi> There are ſtrange men and women Church-members this day, ſtrange children indeed; Ile ſay no more of them, the wicked ſing, a wonderfull <hi>and horrible thing is committed in the Land,</hi> that is, in the Church: what is that? read <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.26, to 30.</p>
                  <p>But what is the moneth here? Is it not ſome change think you, as the Moon doth every moneth? Sure <hi>the next change or turn of things will overturn all the Churches,</hi> for a <hi>third overturn will be:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ezek. 21.27.</note> The firſt was of <hi>Kingly Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative</hi> by the Parliament, then the <hi>Prelates</hi> fell; the ſecond was of <hi>Parliamentary Priviledges,</hi> when the Army came up to purge it, then <hi>Presbyters</hi> fell: there will be a <hi>third overturn,</hi> whether for better or worſe I know not, yet I hope well of the Common-wealth, and Rulers thereof, but down goe the ruling Elders with all their Churches, the very next moneth, when a change of things will be.</p>
                  <p>But thirdly, May not <hi>this moneth</hi> be another thing, yet ſomething more?
<note place="margin">Pſal. 119.96.</note> (for the <hi>Commands of God are exceeding broad,</hi> and there is a mighty bredth, height, and length in the leaſt word of his) what is the <hi>moneth?</hi> Is it not the <hi>new Moon</hi> ſpoken of ſo much by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, as a type of that <hi>new Moon and Sabbath</hi> which ſhall be in the <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi> Iſai. 66.22, 23.</p>
                  <p>What is the <hi>new Moon</hi> then? Truly to me it is <hi>new Light,</hi> as <hi>our life in God alone is the Sabbath</hi> there ſpoken: oh how terrible is this to the Paſtors and Teachers to look for <hi>new light,</hi> much more to look on it, it will dazle and deſtroy their ſight, and make them ſtark blind, and alſo dumb, as we ſhall ſee anon.</p>
                  <p>Every <hi>moneth</hi> we know the <hi>Moon</hi> receives <hi>new light</hi>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:118421:28"/>as we call it, then the <hi>new Moon,</hi> though it be the old ſtill; ſo the <hi>new light</hi> is nothing but the old, even the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> that <hi>glory hid in God before the world,</hi> will come <hi>forth in men</hi> at laſt; yea, that <hi>old light of Law and Goſpel-Churches,</hi> which hath been <hi>hid</hi> and darkened by the Apoſtacy, ſhall be more fully known, and come forth from all that traditionall knowledge of God which is yet received by men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 10.23.</p>
                  <p>Oh this <hi>moneth</hi> will be a <hi>day of doom</hi> to the Churches, the <hi>new Moon,</hi> this <hi>new light,</hi> will darken them at <hi>noon day;</hi> pray read <hi>Amos</hi> 8.9. where there is a greater than this yeares Eclipſe, the earth is not onely darkened at noon, but <hi>the Sun goes down, and ſets at high noon:</hi> What is that? When men think they are in <hi>higheſt light,</hi> as Churches look no higher, God doth ſuddenly <hi>darken them,</hi> and makes them alſo <hi>dumb,</hi> verſe 11. for there is none left to preach the Word, being no more to be heard from North to Eaſt, verſe 12. from <hi>Scotland</hi> to <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Wales.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Why is all this wrath think yee? <hi>The end is come upon my people Iſrael,</hi> that is the Church, verſe 2. then there is the <hi>howling of the Shepheards,</hi> and their <hi>ſilencing,</hi> verſe 3.</p>
                  <p>This is wrath indeed, but what is the cauſe of all? Sure firſt becauſe the Churches <hi>take no care for the poor of the Land,</hi> verſe 4. they may look to their own poor, but the poor of the Land <hi>are ſwallowed up</hi> by their ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and made to fail, for the Miniſters will not open their mouths, nor ſpeak a good word for them to the preſent Governours, who doubtleſſe would and will help the poor at laſt, though never moved by the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
                  <p>But ſecondly, They cannot abide <hi>new light,</hi> therefore darkneſſe comes as we ſaid, <hi>when will the new Moon be gone,</hi> ſay they, or as the margin reads, the <hi>new Moneth?</hi> this kills the Paſtors and Teachers, this <hi>one Moneth</hi> cuts them off by God.</p>
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:118421:28"/>
                  <p>But why would they have <hi>this new Moon gone, and the Sabbath paſt?</hi> Oh that they may <hi>ſell Corn, and ſet forth Wheat,</hi> verſe 5. for there is no buying nor ſelling, nor a ſtitch of work to be done on the <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wheat, what is that? <hi>What is the Chaffe to the Wheat,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 23.28.</note> ſaith the Prophet? Wheat ſure is the <hi>pure Word,</hi> called the <hi>fat of the Kidneyes of Wheat,</hi> and ſo the <hi>pure word</hi> is,
<note place="margin">Deut. 32.14.</note> it is the fineſt fattening thing that man can take, that <hi>immontall ſeed of the Word, when it is ſincere, ſpirituall, and pure,</hi> how pretious, and how powerfull it is? But <hi>what is the Chaffe to the Wheat? Chaffe</hi> hath the form and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of <hi>Wheat,</hi> but it goes away with the wind, yea, the <hi>Fan of the Lord,</hi> or any <hi>ſufferings from men,</hi> as I ſaid before, blowes away the Chaffe, both the Word and the Preachers of it.</p>
                  <p>But ſuppoſe <hi>it be Wheat that they ſell?</hi> it is but the <hi>refuſe of Wheat, as themſelves confeſſe, Amos.</hi> 8.6. what lean, low, and legall teachings doe our Preachers of the Goſpel ſet forth and ſell? it is but <hi>the refuſe of all,</hi> that which good Mr. <hi>Perkins,</hi> Doctor <hi>Preſton,</hi> and the reſt of thoſe pious men left behind; it is not <hi>their ſpirit</hi> theſe men ſpeak with, it is but their words, or the lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of old Writers in a new dreſſe.</p>
                  <p>Nay moſt of theſe Paſtors or Preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel can goe no farther than the <hi>fleſh of Chriſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">A cheif one of the Army would once uſually ſay, that the <hi>fleſh of Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>letter of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> were the two great I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dols of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Iohn 6.63. Heb. 4.12.</note> and the <hi>letter of Scripture,</hi> as for that <hi>eternall Spirit</hi> which dwelt in the one, and which ſpake in the other, they know not; <hi>the fleſh profiteth nothing,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, it is <hi>the Spirit that quickeneth, the words that I ſpeak are Spirit and life:</hi> where is that ſpirituall, <hi>quick, and lively words? Spirit and life it ſelf</hi> miniſtred to men, and in them?</p>
                  <p>Is it not the <hi>refuſe of Wheat that they ſell?</hi> when all that is ſold by them is not worth the knowledge of a Chriſtian? <hi>Henceforth,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>know we no man after the fleſh, yea, though we have known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet now henceforth know we him no more,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.16. We know not Chriſt now, ſaith he, but <hi>God in Chriſt,</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:118421:29"/>verſe 19. for ſo Chriſt would be known, onely as the <hi>Fathers Image,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ioh, 14.9, 10.</note> 
                     <hi>he that ſees me ſees the Father, if thou hadſt known me thou wouldſt have known the Father,</hi> it was God even the Father who was all in all in his fleſh, <hi>who did all, and ſpake all, in him, and by him;</hi> he was indeed <hi>the way to the Father,</hi> not that men ſhould <hi>ſtand ſtill in Chriſt,</hi> as I ſaid before, but by him <hi>goe to the Father, and with him dwell in God;</hi> ſo he was the <hi>truth,</hi> becauſe the <hi>everlaſting Father,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.18.</note> 
                     <hi>the onely true God, ſent the Son,</hi> or came forth in fleſh, and crucified it alſo to himſelf, to <hi>bring men to God,</hi> and thus Chriſt was <hi>the life,</hi> and our life alſo.</p>
                  <p>For indeed, <hi>all the life, knowledge, and faith of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, by Chriſt as the way, doth tend and end in God,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.21. Yet this is not all, and yet this the Paſtors and Teachers know not;
<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.17.</note> for <hi>if any man be in Chriſt he is a new Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> or as the Greek reads, a <hi>new Creation;</hi> why, the greateſt of them all goe no higher than the <hi>firſt Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as I ſaid before.</p>
                  <p>But again, <hi>God in Chriſt, and Chriſt in men, is a Myſtery yet that none of the Miniſters of Churches can manifeſt to the world,</hi> thoſe <hi>hidden Myſteries,</hi> and <hi>Secrets of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> that high <hi>Myſtery of God even the Father, and of Chriſt, and the Myſtery of the Goſpel,</hi> theſe Miniſters of the Goſpel know not, as I ſhall ſhew (with God) ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time.</p>
                  <p>But now ſee what <hi>Merchants</hi> we have in the world, mark it, <hi>they ſell Wheat,</hi> nay, ſhame upon them, they ſell <hi>the refuſe of Wheat, and ſell it; for what?</hi> at the higheſt rate that ever was, <hi>the refuſe of Wheat,</hi> an <hi>old Sermon,</hi> that is even mouldy with lying by, they will not part with without a price, yea, they ſell it them at a dear rate, none will preach now under a hundered pound a year, teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is turned to a meer Trade, he that will give moſt ſhall moſt Goſpel, under the Law all the Prieſts had but the like allowance, Goſpel-Miniſters preached freely, yet wanted nothing, now men will not truſt God, but
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:118421:29"/>muſt have beforehand, ſome twenty ſhillings for every Sermon they make, ſome fortie ſhillings a Sermon, yea, there are Paſtors and Teachers in <hi>England,</hi> who have four pound for every Sunday Sermon, beſides four pound every week, for government and gaudies, or eating good cheer.</p>
                  <p>Doe not theſe <hi>make merchandiſe of the Word of God?</hi> are not theſe <hi>the Merchants which</hi> John <hi>ſpeaks that ſhall ſhortly cry, alas, alas?</hi> Rev. 18.15.
<note place="margin">Rev. 18.15.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>Was there ever the like heard in the world, <hi>that the refuſe of wheat ſhould be ſold ſo dear</hi> by Divines and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual men?</p>
                  <p>Spiritual men ſaid I? What they who are imployed in Secular and Martiall affaires?</p>
                  <p>I doe not blame the Governours of our State, for ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting ſuch honour and preferment on the heads of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers, <hi>Conſtantine</hi> did more, yet more miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief followed, and the <hi>Church as they ſay, fell aſleep in</hi> Conſtantines <hi>lap,</hi> ſo I wiſh the wiſe and godly Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of the Common-wealth to conſider:</p>
                  <p>I pray conſider, is it according <hi>to the order of the Goſpel,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 20.28.</note> that Paſtors ſhould leave their own <hi>Church-fellowſhips,</hi> and turn <hi>fellows of Colledges?</hi> Is it according to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel that Paſtors ſhould become Princes and Preſidents, Deans and Doctors? Is not this a ſecular imployment? and this in the hands of ſpirituall men, is but the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments <hi>of a fooliſh Shepherd,</hi> as the Lord General <hi>Crom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel</hi> excellently words it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>This is the great hand of God, and worthy of the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of all thoſe (Miniſters) who taking into their hands the Inſtruments of a fooliſh Shepherd, to wit, medling with worldly policies, and mixtures of earthly power, to ſet up that which they call the Kingdome of Chriſt, which is neither it, nor if it were, would ſuch meanes be found effectunll for that end, and neglect or not truſt to the word of God, the ſword of the Spirit,</hi> &amp;c. A Letter from <hi>Dumbar,</hi> p. 11.</p>
                  <p>That this is not a ſpiritual but a <hi>ſecular</hi> power, or
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:118421:30"/>
                     <hi>earthly mixture</hi> appears becauſe an Univerſitie is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the School of Nature elevated and improved by Art, not by Religious forms (though the power of it be precious) but by excellencie of learning which Paſtors and Teachers are not much acquainted with, ſo were fitter men.</p>
                  <p>Again, It is a very ſad <hi>Omen</hi> when Miniſters of the Goſpel, and Paſtors of Churches creep ſo faſt into Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, not onely becauſe <hi>the proſperitie</hi> (or eaſe) <hi>of fools deſtroys them,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Prov. 1.32.</note> but it is the <hi>Geneva</hi> Note on <hi>Acts</hi> 6.12. That the firſt bloudie <hi>Perſecution of the Church of Chriſt ſprang up and began from a company of Prieſts by the ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie Doctors.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But we are gone too far from Market, we heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their <hi>ſelling the refuſe of Wheat for Silver;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Amos 8.6.</note> I tell you there is more in that Verſe: <hi>They buy the poor for Silver, and the needie for a pair of ſhooes:</hi> Or as the ſame Prophet ſpeaks,
<note place="margin">Amos 2.6.</note> 
                     <hi>They ſell the righteous for ſilver, and the poor for a pair of ſhooes.</hi> That is, if there be a righteous poor man that ſeeks the publike good <hi>of the Common-wealth,</hi> or the <hi>good of mankind,</hi> they will either keep him poor, or make him rich, they will ſtop his mouth with a <hi>piece of ſilver,</hi> or ſend him away in a <hi>pair of ſhooes.</hi> Whats that? ſet him in a <hi>good office,</hi> or <hi>gainfull imployment,</hi> thats <hi>a pair of ſhooes</hi> that many an honeſt heart is bought and ſold for.</p>
                  <p>I wonder that the Prophet ſhould ſay of God, <hi>Thou haſt forſaken thy people the houſe of Jacob,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 2.7.</note> &amp;c. <hi>Why? Their land is full of filver and gold, and there is no end of their trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Truly it were well the tidings had bin true, That we Chriſtians would have no more ſilver and gold from the <hi>Indies,</hi> then gold ſhould not be our God: But now I fear me that <hi>Mammon</hi> is not onely the <hi>god</hi> of the world, but the god of Churches alſo, yea many good Chriſtians make Mammon and money their God.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:118421:30"/>
                  <p>In the Apoſtles dayes, <hi>The love of money was the root of all evill,</hi> it lay cloſe in the Earth, but now it is <hi>riſen to a Tree</hi> all men may ſee that money is moſt loved by good and bad alike.
<note place="margin">Ezek. 7.10.11</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of a <hi>cloaked covetouſneſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 2.5.</note> it was much co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered and kept cloſe then, becauſe indeed the Churches were ſo pure and poor, but now covetouſneſſe walks a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad by day without any cloak ſtark naked, that all doe ſee and cry ſhame on the Saints this day?</p>
                  <p>Oh the <hi>hour of Temptation is come upon all them that dwell on the earth;</hi> True, that <hi>dwell on the earth;</hi> yea,
<note place="margin">Rev. 3.10.</note> thoſe who <hi>dwell in heaven</hi> are tempted with it alſo, the glory of the <hi>world was the laſt and greateſt of all Chriſts Temptations,</hi> Matth. 4.8.</p>
                  <p>I doe not envie your greatneſſe (God knows) but pitty your goodneſs that is ſo beſieged with great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Worldly glory, with Silver, and Gold, and Money, and more then <hi>heart could wiſh,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 73.7.</note> the Lords and Nobles of old could doe better with it becauſe Gentlemen born, but when ſo much money comes into the hands of poor Saints, oh, how they hold it, and hug it, and hunger after more, as dogs after dry hones. Woe, woe to the Churches, and Chriſtians this day. Truly Friend, I was forced as firſt to ſpeak, then to write, ſo now to publiſh theſe things to the world.</p>
                  <p>I would much rather have been at home, and ſate in ſilence, yea better had it been for my fleſh and family, if I had (as I ſaid) even enter <hi>into my chambers,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſai. 26.20.</note> 
                     <hi>and ſhut the door upon me untill the Indignation bee overpaſt,</hi> that is, till all the ſeven Vials full of wrath be poured forth; there is wrath enough on the Churches already, their own diviſions would deſtroy them quick enough; and why then muſt I come forth like a fool, and put my head between their blows.</p>
                  <p>But yet God hath appointed a worm to pour out wrath on the Churches, to pour out wrath, and yet in love, to lye under the ſame wrath with them, and for
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:118421:31"/>their ſake to ſuffer this, for he that kills with the <hi>ſword, ſhall be killed by the ſword,</hi> Rev. 13.10. 'Tis not my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs then, but <hi>Woe is me my mother, that thou haſt made me a man of contention to all the earth,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ier. 15.10.</note> &amp;c. Firſt, to Prelates. then to Presbyters, now to Independent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors and Teachers; It is my <hi>mother the Church</hi> hath made me thus, for my Fathers Spirit, the promiſe of the Father in me doth teach me better things.</p>
                  <p>There are better things indeed that the Saints ſhould wait for, things above Law and Goſpel-order, if it were as it was,
<note place="margin">Ier. 50.45.</note> but is not, things which neither Prophets, nor Apoſtles attained to, yet both did write of, and wait for,
<note place="margin">Rom. 8.21.</note> 
                     <hi>the glory to be revealed in us,</hi> the <hi>glorious libertie of the ſons of God,</hi> and of the ſons of men alſo, even of the <hi>whole Creation;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.13.</note> the <hi>new Heaven</hi> and <hi>new Earth,</hi> the <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.2.</note> the <hi>appearance</hi> of the great God in us, when <hi>we ſhall be like him, and ſee him as he is, ſee his face, and his name on our foreheads,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 22.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c.</note> when there ſhall be <hi>no curſe, nor cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, nor death;</hi> but the <hi>tree of life</hi> in the midſt of us, the River of <hi>life, cleer as Cryſtall</hi> proceeding out of the Throne of God and the Lamb that is in us:
<note place="margin">Zach. 14.8. Job 20.17. Ioel 3.18.</note> Theſe are the <hi>living waters,</hi> the Rivers and Brooks of <hi>butter and honey</hi> the Prophets ſpeak of, yea, the <hi>mountains dropping down new wine, and the hills flowing with milk</hi> is more then was in Goſpel-times,
<note place="margin">Acts 2.</note> the <hi>new wine,</hi> the Spirit which the Apoſtles were drunk with at firſt, was but the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> but a taſte of that which ſhall be more fully drawn forth in the laſt dayes,
<note place="margin">Zach. 9.15. Rev. 19.6.</note> when men <hi>ſhall drink and make a noiſe as through wine, and be filled with bowls,</hi> &amp;c. yea, make a noiſe <hi>as of thunder, being the voice of much people in heaven,</hi> and of many Allelujahs. Thoſe who ſhall ſing and ſpeak really and indeed theſe <hi>gladtidings to men</hi> ſhall not want <hi>money</hi> nor <hi>meanes,</hi> for <hi>City and Country</hi> (and <hi>Kings</hi> too) ſhall contribute their <hi>glory to them,</hi> the <hi>City Merchant</hi> ſhall give them food and raiment, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 23.18. and Country Farmers ſhall ſerve their wives and children to plow ſow, and reap for them, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 61.4, 5, 6, and 9. verſes, yea,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:118421:31"/>the Lord God himſelf will be ready as a ſervant,
<note place="margin">Iſai. 45.11. Iſai. 58.9.</note> to wait <hi>on them at their command, and at their call</hi> (<hi>Here am I,</hi> ſaith he) <hi>to thoſe who undoe the heavie burthens, and let the oppreſſed goe free, and break every yoke</hi> (from mens ſtates and ſpirits) this the everlaſting Goſpel will doe, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 58.6, 7, 8, 9, 12. verſes compared.</p>
                  <p>This is alſo the <hi>Sabbath</hi> before ſpoken of (which the Miniſters there wiſh it were over) not onely to <hi>ceaſe from our own works,</hi> but from ſpeaking our <hi>own words,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 4.10. Iſai. 58.13.</note> or from <hi>ſpeaking words</hi> as the Hebrew reads, <hi>v.</hi> 13.
<note place="margin">Heb. 22.19.</note> The Law in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed was <hi>a voice of words,</hi> and the preaching of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel at firſt, was in this far below its own light, at leaſt below that glory of the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel</hi> at laſt, which ſhall not be in <hi>words</hi> or ſpeakings,
<note place="margin">Rev. 19.8. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> but in the righteous actings of men, the <hi>righteouſneſſes of Saints,</hi> Rev. 19.8. The <hi>Angel</hi> who is to preach the <hi>everlaſting Goſpel,</hi> is no particular man, or men (as in the <hi>Goſpel-Miniſtry</hi> at firſt) but the Spirit it ſelf, even the <hi>glorious appearance of the great God</hi> in Men, and in Magiſtrates firſt ſhall Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter that <hi>light and love and glory to bee revealed</hi> in us. Thus the <hi>Angel flyes in the midſt of heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Rev. 14.6. the other Angel <hi>v.</hi> 7. is another appearance of God in men.
<note place="margin">Revel. 21.24.</note> For as the <hi>Kings of the Earth bring their glory</hi> and honour <hi>to the New Jeruſalem,</hi> (that of the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> being the ſum of the everlaſting Goſpel) ſo theſe <hi>Kings of the earth</hi> who ſhall be, are the <hi>ten Kings who burn the whores fleſh with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ten Kings</hi> are not a Kingly power, for Monarchy will never burn Miniſtery, (the whores fleſh) but ſuch a government of men, <hi>who have received no Kingdome as yet, but receive power as Kings one hour with the Beaſt, Rev.</hi> 17.12. as the two Beaſts are falſe Miniſtery under ſeverall forms, ſo the Beaſt here is the ſecond Beaſt, (
<note n="*" place="margin">The Beaſt and the <hi>falſe Prophet were taken,</hi> &amp;c. The Beaſt is the firſt Beaſt, the falſe Prophet is the ſecond Beaſt <hi>who did Miracles.</hi>
                     </note> called the falſe Prophet, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20.) who hath two <hi>hornes like a lambe,</hi> this being the pureſt Miniſterie, and moſt like <hi>Chriſt,</hi> though indeed of Antichriſt, <hi>doing and ſpeaking as the Dragon and firſt Beaſt did,</hi> Rev. 23.11, 12.</p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:118421:32"/>
                  <p>To this ſecond Beaſt the <hi>ten Kings with one mind give their power and ſtrength,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rev. 13.14. Rev. 19.20. compared.</note> 
                     <hi>and make war with the Lamb,</hi> oppoſe and perſecute the high appearance of God in his <hi>ſuffering Saints,</hi> who are ſaid to be <hi>with him, who</hi> alſo <hi>by ſuffering ſhall overcome</hi> at laſt, both the <hi>Beaſt and ten Kings</hi> with him, <hi>Rev,</hi> 17.13, 14. compared with <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.11.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>ten Kings</hi> being thus <hi>overcome</hi> by the Spirit of the Lord in his people (and by the ſame Spirit appearing in themſelves) ſhall hate <hi>the whore</hi> (with the Beaſt) and <hi>ſhall burn her fleſh with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16.</p>
                  <p>But before this (as I ſaid) they had <hi>given their power to the Beaſt,</hi> the reaſon why they gave it is ſtrange, and ſhould ſtill all the murmurings of men: <hi>For God put it in their hearts to fulfill his will; and to agree, and to give their Kingdom to the Beaſt, untill the words of God ſhall be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> Rev. 17.17.</p>
                  <p>When the words of God are fulfilled, then the <hi>woman</hi> (that <hi>whoriſh ſpirit</hi> or dependance on Men and Miniſters which reigns <hi>over the Kings of the earth</hi>) the ten <hi>Kings ſhall burn with fire,</hi> that is, by the power and Spirit of the Lord God appearing in them as <hi>Fire.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe ten Kings then ſeem to me to be a <hi>State Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> (like ours) who have no <hi>Kingdom as yet</hi> (not yet ſetled) though the Beaſt may make them believe <hi>they are Kings for an hour,</hi> for that little time of the Beaſts reign over them, but the <hi>Kings can doe nothing,</hi> they can doe no more nor longer, then the <hi>Lord puts in their hearts,</hi> as was ſaid before, therefore when the <hi>Word of God is ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled,</hi> and his time accompliſhed, The <hi>ten Kings</hi> (though formerly ruled by <hi>the Beaſt,</hi> and loving <hi>the whore,</hi> yet now) <hi>hate her, make her deſolate, and naked, eat her fleſh, and burn her with fire,</hi> Rev. 17.16, 17.</p>
                  <p>[How beloved were the Biſhops or Prelates to moſt of the <hi>preſent powers,</hi> in whom yet ſuch a Spirit ſince appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that hath burnt up all thoſe, and will them that follow.]</p>
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:118421:32"/>
                  <p>Thoſe <hi>Kings then who bring their glory and honour to the new Jeruſalem,</hi> are the <hi>ten Kings,</hi> and theſe <hi>ten Kings</hi> are the Chriſtian Magiſtrates (it may be ours) for as the <hi>Nations of them that are ſaved</hi> are joyned with them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. ſo theſe <hi>three Nations</hi> I beleeve will be the firſt <hi>ſaved ones</hi> in the world, from Monarchy, and Tyranny, and <hi>Babylons</hi> captivity, from all Oppreſſion and Bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage on mens States and Spirits.</p>
                  <p>The ſumme of all is this, That the Appearance of God in the Chriſtian Magiſtrate alſo, will goe forth as the flying Angel, &amp;c. 2. That fire whereby they burn the Whores fleſh; is the Spirit of the Lord God in them. 3. That Spirit which appeared in the Miniſters of Chriſt preaching the Goſpel at firſt, will now appear in the Chriſtian Magiſtrate much more at laſt. 4. As the <hi>Magiſtrate</hi> is the <hi>Miniſter of God,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> and the onely true Miniſter now (there being none in the Church) ſo God in the laſt dayes will firſt appear with power and glory, not in the Church, but in the Common-wealth, not in Miniſters at all, but in the Magiſtrate both Civill and Martiall.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Lord will ſave the Tents of Judah firſt,</hi> Zach. 12.7. And <hi>the Governours of Judah ſhall ſay in their hearts, the</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>The Inbabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> are thoſe who have the high diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of God dwelling in them, theſe are the ſtrength of the State, the <hi>Chariots and Horſemen of Iſrael,</hi> as the Generall ſpeaks anon.</note> 
                     <hi>Inhabitants of Jeruſalem ſhall be my ſtrength in the Lord their God,</hi> verſe 5. Again, <hi>I will make thine Officers peace, and thine Exactors righteouſneſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Iſai. 60.17, 18.</p>
                  <p>Indeed if any man doth but obſerve and follow the foot-ſteps of the Almighty this day, in his wayes and wonders among men, his glorious Appearance, and his Power, and Goodneſſe in this Land hath been moſt viſible to, and by the Magiſtrate Civill and Martiall, at home and abroad, both by land and ſea, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>Alas, what have the Miniſters done, but undone themſelves and others? and ſtill like to undoe the whole Nation, as the Prelates in the firſt warre, the Presbyters in the ſecond warre, and though a third warre will not be, yet the proſperity, peace, and happy proceedings
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:118421:33"/>of the preſent Powers, how had the Independent and Baptized Churches like to hinder? how ſaucy and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent were they about a new Repreſentative? yea, no Parliament men, but Church-members, or choſen by them, was once in print: it is more obſervable, thoſe Churches who could never communicate, nor come to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether before, became as one Congregation, to divide and undoe the Common-wealth if poſſibly they could.</p>
                  <p>Well ſaid noble Generall again. <hi>We pray you own his people more and more, for they are the Chariots and Horſemen of Iſrael, diſown your ſelves, but own your authority and power to curb the proud and the inſolent, ſuch as would diſturb the tranquility of</hi> England, <hi>under what ſpecious pretences ſoever; reltive the oppreſſed, hear the groanes of the Priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in</hi> England (when Lord God holy and true, and a Treaſury for the poor?) <hi>Be pleaſed to reform the abuſes of all Profeſſions, and if there be any one that makes many poor to make a few rich, that ſuits not a Common-wealth:</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Heu quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus inane?</hi> that is, A thing well ſaid, then done, when power is in thine hand, Would bleſſe thy ſoul, wife, children, and the land.</note> very well ſaid indeed. The Lord Generall <hi>Cromwels</hi> Letter from <hi>Dumbar,</hi> pag. 10.</p>
                  <p>How many <hi>men are made poor,</hi> by making a few <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters rich?</hi> therefore there is but little good done by the <hi>greateſt Miniſters</hi> this day in <hi>England and Ireland;</hi> their whole work is in calling men to <hi>Church, not to Chriſt,</hi> in converting <hi>Saints, not Sinners:</hi> alas man, it is not the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> but thine own <hi>gain</hi> thou moſt lookeſt after.</p>
                  <p>That which you hear of ſo many <hi>called in Wales,</hi> is not ſo true as the report, it is but <hi>to Church</hi> that multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes run, and moſt to <hi>the waters,</hi> but alas poor ſoules, they are ſtill as ſimple and earthly as ever they were, as ignorant, carnall, and covetous, as little power of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, or knowledge in the Myſtery of Chriſt, ſelf-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyall, ſincerity, and ſingleneſſe of heart: oh they are more double and divided, that light and love which was formerly in <hi>Wales</hi> in good Mr. <hi>Wroth</hi>'s dayes, is dead with him, and quite darkened.</p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:118421:33"/>
                  <p>When will the Lord take away the <hi>reproach of his people</hi> from off all the earth? <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 25.8.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>They know not to doe right, ſaith the Lord, who ſtore up violence and robbery in their Palaces,</hi> Amos 3.10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Are yee not as children of</hi> Aethiopians <hi>unto me, oh yee children of Iſrael?</hi> Amos 9.7, 10.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>He is Canaan</hi> (ſaith the margin) <hi>or a Merchant, the ballances of deceit are in his hand, be loveth to oppreſſe,</hi> Hoſ. 12.7.</p>
                  <p>What <hi>Merchants</hi> the <hi>Miniſters</hi> are of the <hi>Word</hi> we have heard before, and what <hi>Merchandize Church-mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers</hi> make of the <hi>World,</hi> the world will ſee very ſhortly.</p>
                  <p>Truly in all that I have ſaid,
<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.15.</note> I doe not <hi>condemn the generation of the Righteous,</hi> but the <hi>generations of Vipers,</hi> who under <hi>formes of Religion</hi> eat up their Mothers bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els, even the <hi>power of Righteouſneſſe,</hi> the <hi>Church of the firſt-born,</hi> yea, <hi>Jeruſalem that is above, which is free, and the Mother of us all coming down from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,</hi> theſe men and Miniſters would hinder and hide in <hi>the Earth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Again, I doe not judge the <hi>Governours of our State,</hi> nor <hi>State Miniſters,</hi> ſent forth by the <hi>power of man,</hi> to civilize and teach the people, to inſtruct the Nation in <hi>peace and holineſſe,</hi> and in
<note n="*" place="margin">There be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing now no <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel</hi> who can goe forth <hi>freely</hi> to the world <hi>with power from on high; State Miniſters</hi> will never doe good till they <hi>gain the hearts of the people to the preſent Powers,</hi> in whom God hath ſo viſibly appeared, that men cannot; chuſe but ſee and be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced; that there is yet <hi>more good to be done by them, and for us,</hi> in Gods due time.</note> 
                     <hi>honourable thoughts of the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which (though yet <hi>clouded under particular cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, and crooching under its own greatneſſe</hi>) will ride on proſperouſly through the three Nations, and riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the Nations round about, in ſpight of all their threats or attempts, yea, (though there may be a black moneth) yet the glory of the Lord ſhall cover it, till the <hi>glorious liberty of the Sonnes of God</hi> (and of Men alſo) ſhall ariſe as the Sun in this <hi>Land</hi> at laſt, as the firſt fruits of freedome, and healing to the world, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.2. compared.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, Let no <hi>Independent Paſtor, nor Presbyters,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing themſelves <hi>Miniſters of the Goſpel,</hi> dare to meddle any more with <hi>Tithes,</hi> forced <hi>Contributions,</hi> or <hi>Conſolida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi>
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:118421:34"/>nor make a <hi>gain of Godlineſſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Tim. 6.5. 1 Tim. 3.3. Iude 11.</note> nor a <hi>Trade of Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> becauſe the <hi>Servant that knowes his Maſters will</hi> and doth it not, ſhall be <hi>beaten with many ſtripes, Luke</hi> 12, 47. that is, the Lord Chriſt will <hi>ſtrip you,</hi> and <hi>whip you</hi> round about the Country.</p>
                  <p>Surely <hi>I come quickly, Amen, even ſo come Lord Jeſus,</hi> oh how <hi>ſuddenly</hi> is he <hi>come to his Temple?</hi> truly brethren the Lord is come, and now making a <hi>Scourge of</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">The leaſt Chriſtians ſhall ſcourge the greateſt Churches. Ier. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0.45. Iohn 2.15.</note> 
                     <hi>ſmall cords, to drive the money changers out of the Temple.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The vile perſon ſhall be no more called liberall, nor the churle ſaid to be bountifull.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the vile perſon ſhall ſpeak vilanny, and his heart will work iniquity, to practiſe hypocriſie, and to utter error againſt the Lord, to make empty the ſoul of the hungry, and he will cauſe the drink of the thirſty to fail.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The inſtruments alſo of the churle are evill, he deviſeth wicked deviſes to deſtroy the poor with lying words, even when the needy ſpeaketh right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>But the liberall deviſeth liberall things, and by liberall things ſhall he ſtand,</hi> Iſaiah 32.5, 6, 7, 8.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
